<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer of the purchasers of the lands, late of Sir John Stawel, by act of Parliament, exposed to sale for his treason to a pamphlet, intituled, The humble remonstrance of Sir John Stawel: together with the answer of John Ashe Esquire, to divers scandals mentioned in that remonstrance. As also a petition and several reasons for establishment of publick sales; tendred by Wil. Lawrence Esq; one of the judges in Scotland.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 204 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75403</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3300</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1072_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208226</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867193</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867193</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119492</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75403)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119492)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 160:E1072[3], 249:E1072[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer of the purchasers of the lands, late of Sir John Stawel, by act of Parliament, exposed to sale for his treason to a pamphlet, intituled, The humble remonstrance of Sir John Stawel: together with the answer of John Ashe Esquire, to divers scandals mentioned in that remonstrance. As also a petition and several reasons for establishment of publick sales; tendred by Wil. Lawrence Esq; one of the judges in Scotland.</title>
                  <author>Lawrence, William, 1613 or 14-1681 or 2.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 61, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Newcomb, dwelling in Thamestreet, over against Baynards Castle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Domini 1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Both an answer to Stawell, John.  To the supreme authority the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England, his excellency the Lord General Cromwell, and his Councell of Officers: the humble remonstrance of Sir John Stawell and to Ashe, John.  An answer to divers scandals mentioned in a certain pamphlet, entituled, The humble remonstrance of Sr. John Stawell.</note>
                  <note>Includes a petition by William Lawrence of Edinburgh.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "ffeb 15:".</note>
                  <note>Errata: final unnumbered page.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stawell, John, --  Sir, 1599-1662. --  To the supreme authority the Parliament of the Common-wealth of England, his excellency the Lord General Cromwell, and his Councell of Officers: the humble remonstrance of Sir John Stawell.</term>
               <term>Ashe, John, --  Esquire. --  Answer to divers scandals mentioned in a certain pamphlet, entituled, The humble remonstrance of Sr. John Stawell.</term>
               <term>Stawell, John, --  Sir, 1599-1662 --  Trials, litigation, etc.</term>
               <term>Confiscation --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119492:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER OF THE PURCHASERS Of the Lands, late of Sir <hi>JOHN STAWEL,</hi> By Act of Parliament, Expoſed to Sale for his TREASON: To a Pamphlet, Intituled, <hi>The humble</hi> Remonſtrance <hi>of Sir</hi> John Stawel: TOGETHER With the Anſwer of <hi>John Aſhe</hi> Eſquire, to divers <hi>Scandals</hi> mentioned in that <hi>Remonſtrance.</hi> AS ALSO A <hi>Petition</hi> and ſeveral <hi>Reaſons</hi> for eſtabliſhment OF PUBLICK SALES; Tendred by <hi>Wil. Lawrence</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> One of the Judges in SCOTLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Newcomb,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Thameſtreet,</hi> over againſt <hi>Baynards</hi> Caſtle, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119492:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119492:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER OF The Purchaſers of the Lands LATE OF Sir JOHN STAWEL; By ACT of PARLIAMENT, Expoſed to Sale for his Treaſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is true, that Affliction and Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities have attended Sir <hi>John Stawels</hi> late condition, not by any practiſe, miſ-information, or ill-grounded Apprehenſions (as himſelf would have it,) but through his own obſtinacy, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs; doubtleſs, as a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for his ſlighting that Mercy, which Divine Providence tendred unto him by the Army; and which, others of his own judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and within his own Articles, timely embracing, did ſafely harbor, whileſt himſelf remains ſplitted on thoſe Rocks which they wiſely avoided. Yet doth he now by his Remonſtrance, proffer his Peaceable-Obedience to this Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, (and it is better late then never.) But of what integrity, can ſuch his Autumn-ſubmiſſion be, ſince it is tendred not till after the Fall of all hopes of a Contrariant, and is mixt with an endeavor to palliat, if not juſtifie his former exorbitances.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119492:3"/>The particulars of which Remonſtrance he doth avow upon the Faith of a Chriſtian, and Honor of a Gentleman, though many of them be notorious untruths; and which Remonſtrance he hath pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed to Vindicate (as he pretendeth) the Honor and Juſtice of the Parliament and Army, and undeceive the People; when divers of them yet feel the ſmart, and others will ever bear the marks of his cruelties.</p>
            <p>It cannot be denied, but that the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> in the year 1640. choſe Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi> to ſerve in Parliament as a Knight there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and thereby intruſted him with the protection of their Eſtates, and Liberties. Which high truſt he undertook, and accordingly ſate in that Parliament; but afterwards, contrary to that truſt, he not onely deſerted that Parliament, but levied war againſt it, and the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Intereſt of that County, by colour of a moſt Illegal Commiſſion of Array; and by the command of one, who as little deſerved the recommendation of the then Houſe of Commons, as Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi> did the choice of that County; neither anſwering the expectation then had of them, and both infringing their Countries truſt.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John</hi> being thus in Arms, oppoſed at <hi>Marſhals-Elm</hi> the Forces then raiſed in that County, by Authority of Parliament, where his catriage will appear by this enſuing Examination, being the Depoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Miniſter of Gods Word, faithful to the Parliament; and one that did, therefore, afterwards ſuffer under Sir <hi>Johns</hi> Tyranny.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <head>October 22. 1650. Examinations taken upon Oath the day and year above written, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Directions from the Right Honorable <hi>The High Court of Juſtice,</hi> concerning certain High Crimes and Miſdemeanors commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Sir <hi>John Stawel,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> for levying War againſt the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>JOhn Daniel</hi> of <hi>Buckland-Mary,</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> Clerk, Aged Sixty years or thereabouts, being ſworn and examined, ſaith, That Sir <hi>John Stawel,</hi> late of <hi>Higham</hi> in the County aforeſaid, Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> did take up Arms againſt the Parliament of <hi>England;</hi> and, to his knowledge, liſted many Soldiers, both Horſe and Foot. And <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1642. the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi> was himſelf in perſon at a place in the ſaid County, called <hi>Marſhals-Elm;</hi> and then and there had many Soldiers under his command, both Horſe and Foot, and did abet and incourage the ſaid Soldiers to fight againſt thoſe that were then near unto them; under the command (as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) of Col. <hi>Pyne</hi> for the Parliament, and preſervation of the Peace of the then Kingdom.</p>
                        <p>And this Examinant further ſaith, That he being with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany that were for the Parliament, did adventure to ride up to the ſaid place of <hi>Marſhals-Elm</hi> by himſelf alone, of purpoſe to diſcern what Forces the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi> had. Before he came full to the top of the Hill, the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> ſtaid him, and asked this Examinant,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119492:3"/>
What he did there, and whether or no he was a Chaplain to the Army? To whom this Examinant replied, That he was not, but had ſome occaſion of his own, at a place called <hi>Shapwick;</hi> which was about two Miles from that place of <hi>Marſhals-Elm.</hi> And being demanded by the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> whether the Round-heads would come up the Hill, and fight them? This Examinant replied, That he believed that they intended not to fight; and thereupon this Examinant deſired him to preſerve the peace of the Kingdom. But the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much enraged, ſwore, That if they would not come up to fight with them, the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> and his Company, would go down the Hill and fight with them; and thereupon drew his ſword, and had alſo a Piſtol, and brandiſhing his ſword, ſaid, Come up Blades, if you have a minde to it, and we are for you.</p>
                        <p>And this Examinant further ſaith, That there were placed in Quar-Pits, thirty Muskettiers or thereabouts, which had their light Matches, and their Muskets loaden, ready to fight; which were at that time en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged by the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> to be valiant.</p>
                        <p>And this Examinant further ſaith, That at that time Mr. <hi>Robert Osborn</hi> (being for the Parliament) was there ſlain, and many others grievouſly hurt and wounded, and this Deponent with others taken priſoners by the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> and his Forces there with him.</p>
                        <p>And this Examinant further ſaith, That one Captain <hi>Roſecareck</hi> (a <hi>Corniſh</hi> man) ſix Moneths after, or thereabouts, came to <hi>Machelny,</hi> where this Examinant then lived, being ſent by the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> and there ſearched this Examinants houſe for Arms, and then carried away a Welſh-hook into the Caſtle of <hi>Taunton;</hi> and alſo divers other Arms from other his Neighbors. And the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> (then calling in the Country upon <hi>Poſſe Comitatus</hi>) by Warrant, ſent for this Examinant to appear before him, and there told him, That he was worthy to be drawn, hanged, and quartered for his ſiding with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament againſt the late King.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>By which Depoſition, the intention of Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> and that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, doth clearly appear to be otherwiſe then what by his <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> is pretended. Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> called the Parliament Forces Round-heads (a Nick-name he lately learnt at Court) ſwore thoſe Round-heads ſhould fight, and then drew and brandiſhed his ſword, inviting them to come up and fight, and encouraged his Muskettiers in the Quar-pit.</p>
            <p>But (ſaith Sir <hi>Iohn</hi>) the Parliament Forces made many ſhots firſt at us, and wounded a Gentleman, and killed his Horſe, which made him, and his, put themſelves into a poſture of Defence.</p>
            <p>Be this granted to be true, (although the Depoſitions on both Parts ſeem to affirm the contrary) yet this Plea <hi>(De ſon Aſſault de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſne)</hi> although it is a good Bar in an Action of Aſſault and Battery. He firſt Aſſaulted me, and therefore I did cut, and gave him thoſe wounds in my own defence. Yet here it is no Plea, ſithence, for a Theif to ſay, The Honeſt-man firſt aſſaulted me, and therefore I rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed him; or for a Traytor to affirm, The Parliaments Forces firſt ſhot at me, and therefore I killed, wounded, and impriſoned them;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119492:4"/>
were never known to be any good Pleas, or ſo much as colourable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes; And Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> being there in Arms againſt the Parliament, was a Treaſon of an high nature. Vain therefore are this and the reſt of Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> pretences in that his Remonſtrance, and of as little weight are his Proteſtations therein, one whereof we now light upon: For he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts before the Almighty God, That he did not cut or draw blood on any man that day; but made it his care to preſerve any of that party, and to reſcue as many as he ſaw any violence offered unto. The truth of which his Proteſtation, will appear by this Depoſition tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <head>October 24. 1650. Examinations taken upon Oath, by virtue of Directions from the Right Honorable <hi>The High Court of Juſtice,</hi> concerning Treaſons, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and other high Crimes and Miſdemeanors committed by Sir <hi>John Stawel,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>NIcholas Ward</hi> of <hi>Chard,</hi> Cordwinder, Aged Thirty five years, or thereabouts, ſworn and examined, ſaith, That about eight years ſince (he was then a Drummer under Lieutenant Colonel <hi>Iohn Preſton,</hi> of the County of <hi>Somerſet;</hi> who raiſed Forces by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority derived from the Parliament, for ſuppreſſing of Inſurrections and Rebellions) This Examinant marched with divers other perſons unto <hi>Marſhals-Elm</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> where appeared Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> with divers other Gentlemen in Arms againſt the Parliament, for the late King, when and where the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Forces were routed by an Ambuſcado laid. And the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> having his ſword drawn, fell on this Examinant, and with his own hand gave him with his ſaid ſword twenty ſix wounds, leaving this Examinant for dead. This Examinant did then ſee the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> ride after the Parliament Soldiers, and hacked and hew'd them This Examinant further ſaith, That the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> did often ſay in this Deponents hearing, That all thoſe that did take up Arms for the Parliament were Rebels, Rogues, and Traytors, and ſhould be all hanged one after another.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>By which Examination, the pretended civility of Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> doth manifeſtly appear, by his hacking and hewing upon the purſuit, and his carbonading of <hi>Nicholas Ward,</hi> a fit expreſſion of that outrage, and would be adjudged ſo, if <hi>Wards</hi> mangled face were in preſent view, his noſe being cut off, and his eye cut out, as <hi>Nicholas Ward</hi> by his Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Court of Articles, and in that Remonſtrance recited, doth ſet forth. But this blood Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> endeavors to wipe off by affirming, That <hi>Ward</hi> having once ſworn and obtained a Judgment againſt him for 100 <hi>l.</hi> damages, findes himſelf now bound to make good that ſhameleſs untruth (ſo he is pleaſed to term it) doubtleſs it is the part of an honeſt man, at all times, and in all places to affirm a truth, eſpecially having ſworn it before a lawful Authority; and therefore
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119492:4"/>
               <hi>Ward</hi> inſerting in his Petition to that Court of Articles, ſuch Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> dealing with him, cannot be any ſcandal, except truth it ſelf be one. For an untruth it cannot now be preſumed: For <hi>Nicholas Ward</hi> in <hi>Hillary</hi> Term, the two and twentieth of <hi>Caroli,</hi> brought his Action of Aſſault and Battery againſt Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> whereunto he pleaded neither this pretended Plea of Self-defence, nor his being compriſed within the Articles of <hi>Exon,</hi> but the general Iſſue of <hi>Not guilty:</hi> Which Iſſue coming to be tryed at an Aſſizes for that County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> the Jury (perſons not intereſſed nor concerned) found him guilty (of this ſhameleſs untruth.) And this very Main being then given in evidence, and proved by one <hi>Checkford,</hi> ſince deceaſed, and other witneſſes (whereof <hi>Ward</hi> himſelf could not be one,) the ſame Jury aſſeſſed ſo great damages as 100 <hi>l.</hi> Without which Teſtimony the Jury would not have found Sir <hi>John</hi> guilty, unleſs they themſelves knew the truth thereof, as perhaps ſome of them did, being Inhabitants of the ſame County. And therefore Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> bare negation, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeeing it tends to the attainting of both Jury and Witneſſes, muſt and will with all unbyaſt perſons beat no weight. Which Sir <hi>John</hi> it ſeems well knew, and therefore produceth ſeveral Certificates and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, in order, as himſelf ſaith, to remove the Grievance which then lay on him by that Petition of <hi>Ward,</hi> (and doubtleſs will lie on him to Succeſſion.)</p>
            <p>And to this Teſtimony Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> gives the title of <hi>Very Honorable,</hi> whereas Neighbor-hood will know how little credit may be given to all thoſe Witneſſes and Certificates, except one of them. Mr. <hi>Emma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel Sandys</hi> his Certificate is firſt produced, which (if admitted) doth make againſt Sir <hi>John</hi> himſelf: For Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi> certifies, that after ſome entercourſe between the Forces, Captain <hi>Preſton</hi> and the Company offering to march up the Hill in two Bodies, the Company on the Hill (meaning Sir <hi>Johns</hi> Company) ſhot at us ſeveral times (meaning the Parliaments Forces) and we at them. Of which words, what other conſtruction can be made then, that Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> Company made the firſt ſhot; and if ſo, where is the truth of Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> Plea of Self-defence. Thus far Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi> (and we muſt believe him, Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> elſe will be angry) hath fixt the ſhameleſs untruth on Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> himſelf, and then proceeds to certifie, That the Parliament Forces flying, Captain <hi>Preſton</hi> and himſelf were taken priſoners, and their Moneys, Horſes, and Weapons taken from them by ſome of Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> Company, who had killed them, if not reſcued by the now Lord <hi>Pawlet</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel.</hi> And theſe priſoners had that night fair Quarters; and for that the Soldiers had taken from them their money, Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman-like, delivered to Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi> Forty ſhillings, which Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi> took for a civil reſpect, and afterwards repaid him with thanks, for his favor and kinde uſage.</p>
            <p>This is the further effect of Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi> Certificate; by which it is obſervable, how ſoon Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> Party had learnt their Trade, firſt to rob, and afterwards to kill; which muſt ſpeak aloud Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> honor, in that he reſcued the priſoners, and gave Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi> Forty ſhillings. Which (for ought appears) might be part of the moneys taken from him, or Captain <hi>Preſton;</hi> and if ſo, Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119492:5"/>
is favored with a Pig of his own Sowe. But where is the Certificate of Captain <hi>Preſton</hi> on this behalf? A perſon of valor, and one that hath faithfully paſſed through the greateſt offices of truſt in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: his Certificate is not to be found, perhaps not demanded, his uſage was ſo bad. It is certified, his Moneys, Horſe, and Arms, were taken from him. And what was the reaſon, that Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> gave Maſter <hi>Sandys</hi> Forty ſhillings, and nothing to Captain <hi>Preſton,</hi> ſeeing both were alike priſoners, alike robbed? Was there no deſign in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality? did not Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> foreſee, or had hopes of a facile, or poſſible corrupting Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi> and his man <hi>Vax,</hi> (to whom he gave ſo liberal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as Fourteen pound) or at leaſt abating their zeal and fidelity to the Parliament? It is certified, That Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi> took it as a civil reſpect and favor; and it was obſerved, That Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi> and his man <hi>Vax,</hi> did thereafter very coldly, if at all engage for the Parliament. And Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi> hath in requital of this reſpect, certified his belief to that Court of Articles, but grounded upon a known untruth; He doth verily believe, That many lives and much blood was that day ſaved by the onely means of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> who then, and at other times, ever behaved himſelf as a lover of his Country.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the words of this bold Certificant, whereas it is too well known in that his Country, That the ſeries of Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> his actions, doubtleſs not unknown to Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi> himſelf, doth ſpeak him the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; witneſs his Depopulations at <hi>Cothelſtone,</hi> and his Planting after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards under colour of ſome ſatisfaction, and through fear of the then Star. chamber, (who began to queſtion ſuch offences) the diſterr'd In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants on the top of <hi>Quantock</hi>-Hill; witneſs thoſe Articles of Complaint by the Town of <hi>Taunton</hi> (the Inhabitants of a whole Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration, and his Neighbors) exhibited againſt him in Parliament, which ſeem to be the Articles mentioned in his Remonſtrance, <hi>P.</hi> 14. to be by that Town preferred. 3 <hi>Car.</hi> againſt him unto the Parliament, upon ſcandalous and falſe ſuggeſtions, as he pretends; and yet they were made good againſt him, and himſelf reproved; and which he hath ſince fully revenged, as will appear. Witneſs his Breach of the Publick Truſt of his Country, by leaving the Parliament (at a time when all the Liberties, and Common-Intereſt of the Subject lay at ſtake) and his taking up of Arms to deſtroy and tyrannize (when thus armed) over the Lives, Liberties, Eſtates, and Conſciences of his Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-Subjects; the very Magiſtrates and High Sheriff himſelf of the County not excepted: And yet Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi> is pleaſed to term him a lover of his Countrey then, at <hi>Marſhals-Elm,</hi> at that time, when Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi> himſelf fighted him (if he fought at all) as a diſturber thereof. <hi>O Regina Pecunia!</hi> What a ſtrange alteration of judgment hath theſe Forty ſhillings wrought in Mr. <hi>Sandys</hi> in a few years!</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> next Proofs are the Examinations of the Lord <hi>Pawlet,</hi> and one <hi>Robert Knight,</hi> Gentleman, (which <hi>Knight,</hi> although not by the title of Gentleman, yet is otherwiſe notoriouſly known in his Country,) both their Depoſitions being to this effect, That Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> did not hurt any man, nor diſcharged his Piſtol, as the Lord <hi>Pawlet</hi> remembers, being near unto him, during all that action, and as Mr.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119492:5"/>
               <hi>Knight</hi> verily believes: Sir <hi>John</hi> not ſtirring out of the highway; and that the Drummer (whom the Lord <hi>Paulet</hi> knoweth not) was (as he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves) not hurt by Sir <hi>John,</hi> but (as he hath ſince heard) by one <hi>Crocker;</hi> which Depoſitions (if true) will no waies invalid <hi>Wards</hi> teſtimony, and much leſs the affirmative and poſitive teſtimony of the witneſſes at the Tryal and Verdict of the Iury thereon, in regard theſe Depoſitions are in the negative, Did not ſtirr out of the highway, nor diſcharge his Piſtol, nor did hurt any man: Whereas it is proved that Sir <hi>John</hi> had his ſword drawn, and <hi>Wards</hi> wounds were given by a ſword, and might be given as well in the highway as in any other place. Neither is it uſual for one Commander to take particular notice of anothers actions, eſpecially in a fight and purſuit of an enemy, and when there was no preintention or cauſe of any ſuch particular obſervation; neither is it improbable but that <hi>Ward</hi> might have that day ſome wounds given him by <hi>Crocker,</hi> and yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards receive 26 more from Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> (all his wounds exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that number) and thoſe by <hi>Crocker</hi> might be given in the Corn, and thoſe by Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> in the highway? The ſame anſwer might be given to the enſuing Depoſitions of <hi>William Stuckly</hi> and <hi>Robert Vax,</hi> being both to the effect of the former; but that the Depoſition of <hi>Vax</hi> is vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary and extra-judicial: and both the Deponents of no ſuch credit in their Country, as in any ſort to call in queſtion the verdict aforeſaid, however by comparing the Depoſitions of <hi>Knight, Stuckly,</hi> and <hi>Vax,</hi> it is evident, that Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> company were by direction and order to, and did give the onſet and charge, which argues Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> actions rather of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive then defenſive, as Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> pretendeth, and the firſt ſhot to be given by his party. The next endeavour of Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> is, by his Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance to extenuate his ſending of <hi>William Cady</hi> and <hi>Iohn England</hi> to <hi>Ivelcheſter</hi> Gaol to eaſe (forſooth) the Caſtle of <hi>Taunton,</hi> whom he there found priſoners, and where they were improperly kept. Tis very true they were improperly impriſoned for their faithfulneſs to the Parliament; and as improperly by Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> by a Mittimus to the Keeper of <hi>Ivelche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> removed from <hi>Taunton</hi> thither.</p>
            <p>But Sir <hi>John</hi> ſaith that he ſoon after releaſed <hi>England,</hi> but could not <hi>Cady,</hi> becauſe he was a priſoner for debt upon his firſt coming thither; but <hi>Cady</hi> ſwears that Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> committed him to the common Goal, and kept him there in chains for a year and more, and threatned to hang him, and ſaid he was a Traitor againſt the King, and demanded 20 <hi>l.</hi> of him, and <hi>Iohn England</hi> doth depoſe, that he taſted very deeply of Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty.</p>
            <p>The Tranſcriptions enſuing are full.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119492:6"/>
                        <head>October 22. 1650. Examinations taken upon Oath the day and year above written, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of directions from the High Court of Iuſtice, concerning certain high crimes and miſdemeanors committed by <hi>Sir Iohn Stawell</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> for levying war againſt the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>IOhn England</hi> of <hi>Taunton,</hi> Clothier, aged thirty years or thereabouts, ſworn and examined, ſaith, That Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> when he was Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of the Town of <hi>Taunton</hi> for the late King againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, did exerciſe much cruelty on ſome of the inhabitants that were real in their affections to the Parliament, by cloſe impriſoning of them, putting by his command, Irons on them, and requiring great Fines from them, to advance the Kings Intereſt to the great deſtruction of the Commonwealth; of which cruelty this Deponent taſted very deeply.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <head>November 5. 1650. An Examination taken at <hi>Dunſter</hi> concerning certain high crimes and miſdemeanors committed againſt the Parliament and Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> by Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> Knight of the Bath.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>VVilliam Cady</hi> of <hi>Dunſter</hi> Mercer, aged 49. years or therea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouts ſworn and examined, ſaith, That the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> did in the year 1644. raiſe Arms againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> and in particular was in a hoſtile poſture of war at a place called <hi>Marſhals Elme</hi> in this County, and there did fight, and there did draw bloud; and ſo continued in arms in the ſaid County againſt the Parliament, and raiſed great ſums of money to aſſiſt the King againſt the Parliament; Committed this Examinant to the common Goal, and there kept him in priſon, and in chains, by the ſpace of one whole year and more, and threatned to hang this Examinant di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times, and ſaid he was a Traitor againſt the King, and did demand ſums of money of him, as he remembers 20 <hi>l.</hi> or more, and further ſaith, that he was carried from the Goal to the Aſſizes for this County, and there was indicted for High Treaſon, and the Bill then found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him. And this Examinant verily believeth, and to his beſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance ſaith, That Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> was then preſent at the ſame Aſſizes.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Will. Cady.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>By which Depoſitions of <hi>William Cady,</hi> it is manifeſt that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> fought and drew blood at <hi>Marſhals Elme;</hi> yet Sir <hi>John Stawels</hi> honorable teſtimony would perſwade, that they believe, he did hurt or wound no man there.</p>
            <p>A very neat belief to mince a truth; as if the wounding of <hi>Ward</hi> to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119492:6"/>
deſperation of life (found ſo by verdict) his hacking and hewing upon the purſuit (proved by <hi>Nicholas Ward</hi>) and his fighting and drawing of bloud (atteſted by <hi>William Cady</hi>) were no hurting of any man. Theſe Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions likewiſe prove the cruelty of Sir <hi>John,</hi> and yet Sir <hi>John</hi> thinks it impoſſible for him to be guilty of ſo much bloud and cruelty as is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Petition of <hi>Cady</hi> and <hi>Ward;</hi> as if 26 wounds draw little or no bloud, and as if chains, irons, cloſe impriſonment, exaction of great fines of well-affected perſons, to advance the late Kings intereſt, to the deſtruction of the Commonwealth (as the inſuing Depoſitions will plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manifeſt) be leſs cruelty then is mentioned in their moderate Petition. We do pray that Sir <hi>John</hi> may no longer ſtand on publick extenuation of theſe and the enſuing outrages of his; but in ſecret repent them, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly imploring the divine mercy, to avoid divine Juſtice, being the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt way to pacifie the reſtleſs proceedings of them, who (as he ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly pretendeth) hate him without a cauſe; but probably are the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of that Juſtice.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Johns</hi> Remonſtrance hath brought us to the year 1643. and to Marquiſs <hi>Hartfords</hi> approach to the Town of <hi>Taunton,</hi> the place which afterward God preſerved amidſt the fires, and notwithſtanding the aduſted wrath and rage of the beſiegers; and which Sir <hi>John,</hi> during his Command thereof, made the Rendezvous of Tyranny and arbitrary power, not to advance the Royal Intereſt (as was divulged) but (as is very likely) to ſatisfie the diſpleaſure he had taken up againſt the Inhabitants thereof, upon the occaſion aboveſaid; upon which approach, theſe faithfull In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants (finding that they were not of ſtrength ſufficient to protect themſelves from this rebellion) ſent their Juſtice of Peace, Mr. <hi>George Powel,</hi> and one Mr. <hi>Nicholas</hi> to the Beſiegers, to Treat of a Rendition upon Articles, during which Treaty, and after Articles agreed on (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which, ſome of them were, That the Inhabitants ſhould be free from Plunder and Impriſonment) the Enemy upon pretence (without the leaſt ground of truth or probability) that the Inhabitants were flying with their Moveables (whereas they were in truth ſome ſtrangers only then in the Town that went out) did enter the ſame, and (notwithſtanding thoſe Articles) plundered it to the value of 10000 <hi>l.</hi> and impriſoned the then Maior, and chief Inhabitants thereof. With what face then can Sir <hi>John</hi> now call ſo loud upon the faith of the Parliament and their Armies to perform their Articles; when himſelf and his aſſociates then brake theirs. Now after this Plunder was made, then Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> (as he ſaith) intreated that the Town might be admitted to a reaſonable Fine, which was aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at 8000 <hi>l.</hi> a ſum which that poor exhauſted Town was not able to pay (the richeſt of them being, before that time plundered to what could be found:) And this moderate Fine was thus impoſed (likely) to the knowledge of Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> (if not by his Vote) for he was then of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of War, that impoſed it, and Governor of the Town: And yet now he ſaith it was 8000 <hi>l.</hi> as he hath heard. To gain which Government, <hi>Walter Cliffe</hi> the Gaoler, <hi>Aldred Seaman,</hi> and others, Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> Agents were ſent to gain ſubſcriptions to the Petition in that Remonſtrance reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted page 13. which Petition was drawn beforehand, and without the knowledge of the Inhabitants; ſome of whom in hopes to get out of priſon, and others for fear of being impriſoned, ſubſcribed the ſame, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119492:7"/>
ſuch as denied their ſubſcriptions thereunto, were by Sir <hi>John Stawels</hi> ſpecial command inhumanly dealt with. Sir <hi>John</hi> having thus gained unto himſelf the Government of this Garriſon, begins his intended re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge on the Inhabitants, labouring with all rigour to extort that fine from them, which he knew to be unreaſonable, and contrary to Articles, to maintain (as he confeſſeth page 16.) the ſouldiers left there in Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, indeed his fellow-Traitors. And ſuch Inhabitants as refuſed to pay the ſame, either through a good affection to the Parliament, or diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, he impriſoned, laid them in irons, threatned to hang them, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied them humane neceſſaries, cauſing a ſpout to be taken away, which ſerved them with rain water for their drink. In which hardſhips Sir <hi>John</hi> kept them untill he had gained from them ſuch ſums of money as he thought fitting; and then ſcoffingly boaſted, that he now knew a way to get money; meaning, by hard impriſonment, and the torment of irons, to inforce men by any means to raiſe ſufficient to ſatisfie him. Neither will his allegation that the Town agreed with the Marquiſs to pay that fine, any way excuſe him, in regard ſuch Compoſition was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their Articles, and made when a plundring ſword was amongſt them. Mr. <hi>George Powel</hi> was then a Juſtice of the Peace in that Town; and how Sir <hi>John</hi> uſed him, his depoſitions and his wifes atteſtation will declare, being as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <head>
                           <hi>October 22 1650.</hi> Examinations taken upon Oath the day and year above written, by vertue of Directions from the right Honorable the High Court of Juſtice, concerning certain high Crimes and miſdemeanors committed by Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> for Levying War againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>GEorge Powel</hi> of <hi>Taunton</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> Gentleman, aged 30 years, or thereabouts, ſworn and examined ſaith, That in or about the fifth day of <hi>June,</hi> in the year 1643. Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> then in company with the Lord Marquiſs of <hi>Hart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and others, entred the ſaid Town of <hi>Taunton</hi> in an hoſtile way (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the day before ſummoned the ſaid Town and Caſtle, for the uſe of the late King) which Town and Caſtle had then declared to be kept for the uſe of the King and Parliament; who after their entring (and ſo by force and power) ſeized on this Deponent with many others, and by one <hi>Davis</hi> their Marſhal, kept him priſoner ſome daies. This Deponent then being of Commiſſion and Iuſtice of the Peace for and within the Town of <hi>Taunton.</hi> And alſo ſaith, That about the eight day of the ſame Month of <hi>Iune,</hi> the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> in company with <hi>Iohn Syms</hi> Eſquire, ſent for, and commanded the ſaid <hi>Davis,</hi> to bring this Deponent before them at the houſe of one <hi>Edward Cooper</hi> in the ſaid Town; who told this Deponent that he was fined eight hundred pounds to the King, for his rebellion againſt the ſaid King: and after many op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrious ſpeeches uſed, ſaying the Parliament and the ſaid Town were a company of Rebels and Traitors againſt the late King, and deſerved to be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119492:7"/>
hanged, required the ſaid Fine of 800 <hi>l.</hi> — of this deponent, and upon his refuſal to pay the ſaid Fine, committed this Deponent cloſe priſoner to the Caſtle of <hi>Taunton,</hi> then in the hands and power of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> as Governour of the ſaid Garriſon for the late King, who after divers weeks impriſonment there, and ſeveral demands of the ſaid Fine, by the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> and refuſal of payment thereof by this Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent; he this Deponent was afterwards by the ſaid command tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Bridewell of <hi>Taunton,</hi> and there kept in Irons cloſe Priſoner (with many others) not ſuffered humane neceſſaries, to the great weakning and impairing of the health of this Deponent; untill at laſt, being often threatned by the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to be hanged; or to be ſent to <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> then in the late Kings power, to be tryed for his life: through fear of which and terrour, and for preſervation of his life, he was conſtrained to Morgage and Pawn that land &amp; credit they had left him, for three hundred pounds or thereabouts; which he paid (then languiſhing in priſon) unto the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell;</hi> to redeem himſelf out of that cruel bondage, and inhumane uſuage and impriſonment.</p>
                        <p>This Deponent further ſaith, that during S. <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi>'s bearing power and government in the ſaid Town; he exacted great ſums of mony from ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral perſons for the late King &amp; his armies uſe: Muſtered Soulderies for the late Kings ſervice againſt the Parliament; and billited and enforced on this Deponent, and divers of the ſaid Town many Soulderies to free quarter. And during his Government there, a Souldier of his Regiment (the name of whom at preſent this Deponent remembreth not) was then hang'd on the Gibbet or Gallowes, ſet upon the Market place in the ſaid Town; and by one <hi>Reeves</hi> his Major, declared that it was the command and pleaſure of the Governour that he ſhould be hanged; which being done, the ſaid <hi>Reeves,</hi> did then further declare openly in the Market place, that it was a beginning, and preſident for the reſt of the Rebels and Roundheads of the Town to look upon, and muſt look ſome of them to follow after ſhortly, or words to that effect, which was to the great terrour and fear of the free-born of this Nation.</p>
                        <div type="part">
                           <p>I <hi>Honour Powell</hi> of <hi>Taunton,</hi> the relict of my late Husband, <hi>George Powell</hi> Gent. am ready to make atteſtation, of what is under written</p>
                           <p>In the time of the late miſeries of this Land, it pleaſed God to make us of this Town, partakers in a great meaſure, of the calamities of the times, of the which my late husband (as is well known) had not the leaſt ſhare; being expoſed to the moſt inhumane cruelties and outrages of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, when this Town was ſubdued by them, and afterwards made the mark of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> envy and hatred (as will more largly appear by what is under written) when he uſurped that moſt Tyrannous govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment over this Town. Firſt of all he impoſed a Fine of eight hundred pounds on him (his houſe being before rifled and plundred by the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dery) for the refuſal to pay the ſaid Fine, he was committed by the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> priſoner to the Caſtle of <hi>Taunton;</hi> after he had lain there a long time, he was removed by his order to the Bridewel; where he was kept cloſe priſoner, and lay night and day in Irons without the leaſt favour; nay denying him that favour, which we give to horſes; namely to have a bundle of clean ſtraw to lye on; ſaying, that he would make him an enſample to all Rogues; and ſhould look through a grate all dayes of his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119492:8"/>
life: and ſaying at his committing to the Bridewell, that he would lay him neck and heels, until he paid his Fine, which words Mr. Maj. of <hi>Taunton</hi> which now is, can atteſt, being in the preſence when they were ſpoken, and threatned at ſeveral other times that he would hang him: Afterwards, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paid a Fine of 300.<hi>l.</hi> of mony beſides what other goods were fetcht from us by his order; he was then releaſed of his impriſonment, being ſo weak, with lying on the ground, and in Irons; that he was ſcarce able to go along the ſtreet; afterwards being ſick, for not hearing one of their malignant Prieſts, on their Monthly Faſt, Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> cauſed him to be brought before him, and fined him 10 <hi>l.</hi> and told him if he did not pay it forthwith, he would levy a greater fine on him, which was forthwith paid unto him; with many more of ſuch like cruelties and threats, which now would be too tedious to recite.</p>
                           <p>One act more of his cruelty, I cannot here in ſilence paſs by; which is this, when he had clapt up my husband cloſe priſoner in the Bridewel, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him in the common priſon, where Felons and other Rogues were kept; he would not ſuffer me; nor yet admit my children, to go unto my husband.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And although Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> by his <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> page 15. ſeems to excuſe Mr. <hi>Powells</hi> impriſonment and detainer, becauſe he found him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and his offence of ſuch a nature, as that he could not be delivered without due courſe of Law. Mr. <hi>Powell</hi> upon his Oath diſcovereth the cauſe of his detainer to be for his affection to the Parliament, and not pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the 800 <hi>l.</hi> impoſed on him for his proportion of that Fine.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Iaſper Chapline,</hi> who was then Maj. of that Town, and a perſon of about 70 years of age will next relate, Sir <hi>Iohn</hi>'s uſuage of him, and the cauſe thereof. His certificate followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <head>Some particulats of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi>'s <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> anſwered, by me <hi>Jaſper Chaplin</hi> the 28 of <hi>Nov.</hi> 1653.</head>
                        <p>When my Lord of <hi>Stanford</hi> firſt entred into the Town of <hi>Taunton,</hi> I being then Major, was commanded with others to ſeize the Caſtle into our hands, for the good and ſafety of the County, which was done acordingly: And ſome of the honourable Deputie Leiutenants of this County, autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed me to receive of divers Delinquents great ſums of money, which I ceived, and paid according to order: but when the Kings army entred this Town, I was wounded in the Knee, and ſent to priſon into the Caſtle; being an old man, and paid a hundred pound Fine; for which I have a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt under Sir <hi>Iohn Stawells</hi> hand. Whilſt I was there in priſon, divers of thoſe of whom I received great ſums of money, became ſuitors to Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to this effect as I remember; that they might be repaid out of my perſonal Eſtate, by whoſe importunity as I conceive, I was ſtill kept in priſon; but how long, I was ſo kept in priſon, I remember not, it being about ten years ſithence, and my ſelf about 80 years of age: as alſo for that I had received of  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                              <desc> _____ </desc>
                           </gap>  
                           <hi>Hellier</hi> of <hi>Exon</hi> 200 <hi>l.</hi> which was thus as I have ſince been informed; he came into this County, ſuppoſing to have remained here in ſome ſafety; but this being known unto the deputy Lieutenants, he was brought unto the Inn, called the <hi>Three Cups</hi> in <hi>Taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton;</hi> &amp; as it ſeems gave bond for paiment of 200. <hi>l.</hi> to be paid unto my ſelf (I not knowing therof until I ſaw the bond) but I received the 200 <hi>l.</hi> and it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119492:8"/>
was thus imployed, the Dep. Leiut. (before that time wanted 200 <hi>l.</hi> (which was procured by my ſelf, Mr <hi>Searl,</hi> and others on our bonds, and repaid accordingly, as by our bonds appeareth. During my impriſonment, my houſe was plundered, and I not left worth ten ſhillings to my knowledge, more then the timber ſtuff, ſo that I loſt 400 <hi>l.</hi> or thereabouts.</p>
                        <p>And Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> came himſelf to the Priſon at my enlargement; but I never found ſuch contentment in priſon, as to deſire the ſaid Sir <hi>Ioh. Stawell,</hi> to ſend me back to priſon again, as is alledged; ſo that for my ſuffering and loſſes, the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> confeſſed me a judgement 313.<hi>l.</hi> as I was informed by my Attorney.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>By me <hi>Jaſper Chaplin.</hi>
                           </signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>And although Sir <hi>John</hi> in his Remonſtrance, <hi>p.</hi> 20. ſeems to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie it, the impriſonment being by his conſent, and for his good, for the Reaſons therein ſet forth; yet doth Mr. <hi>Chaplin</hi> deny any ſuch conſent, or any contentment in his impriſonment, to induce either his deſire thereof, or conſent thereunto. Indeed his great Age could take no delight in, nor endure any impriſonment; but the truth was, he was detained by Sir <hi>John,</hi> until he had paid a conſiderable proportion of that moderate Fine. And although it ſhould be granted, That he was impriſoned in ſuch manner, and for thoſe curteous ends mentioned in that place of his Remonſtrance, yet Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> had no Authority, nor Reaſon ſo to do; no Authority we know, nor Reaſon, himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth: For as he ſaith, he wrote unto Prince <hi>Maurice,</hi> That it was contrary to Reaſon, to enforce that from him (meaning Mr. <hi>Chaplin,</hi> who was admitted to his Compoſition) which he was liable to repay unto his Creditors. But Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> did firſt impriſon Mr. <hi>Chaplin,</hi> and then return an Anſwer to the Prince; whereas, it had perhaps been more juſt, firſt to have endeavored the Princes ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Matthew Quaſh,</hi> Mr. <hi>William Milles,</hi> Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Taylor,</hi> Mr. <hi>John Adams,</hi> Mr. <hi>Evans,</hi> Mr. <hi>Andrew Pit,</hi> Mr. <hi>George Treagle,</hi> Mr. <hi>William Cady,</hi> Mr. <hi>Iohn England,</hi> Mr. <hi>Alexand Kingſland,</hi> Mr. <hi>George Lyſſant,</hi> and others of the chiefeſt Inhabitants ſuffered likewiſe under him; ſome of whom were ſo much weakned by their impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ill-uſage therein, that they were not well able to go out again: All which, theſe Oaths and Certificates will manifeſt.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="deposition">
               <body>
                  <head>The Information of <hi>John Adams</hi> of <hi>Taunton,</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> Gentleman, taken upon Oath before Sir <hi>William Rowe,</hi> Knight, <hi>George Manby</hi> and <hi>William Weſton,</hi> Eſquires. A Committee of Examinations appointed by <hi>The High Court of Juſtice,</hi> the <hi>12</hi> day of <hi>December, 1650.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>Who ſaith,</opener>
                  <p>HE hath known Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> by the ſpace of ſixteen years and upwards, laſt paſt; and that in <hi>Iune</hi> in or about the 19 year of the Reign of the late King: He know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, That the ſaid <hi>Stawel</hi> was in <hi>Taunton</hi> with Prince <hi>Maurice,</hi> and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119492:9"/>
Marqueſs <hi>Hertford;</hi> and about a week after, he was in <hi>Taunton,</hi> and acted there as the Governor; and ſent Summons to this Informant under his hand, to appear before him; where being come, the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> commanded him to provide One hundred pounds for the late Kings ſervice; whereof one Fifty pounds he demanded in hand, and the other ſhortly after. Which ſaid One hundred pounds was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on this Informant, as his part of Eight thouſand pounds im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed as a Fine upon the ſaid Town of <hi>Taunton,</hi> for their Rebellion (as the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> termed it) againſt the ſaid late King, by their adhering to the Parliament. Which Money, this Informant refuſed to pay, and was therefore committed priſoner, by Warrant under the Hand of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> to the Caſtle of <hi>Taunton,</hi> where he remained about ten days, until his wife had borrowed Fifty pounds, and paid it to the ſaid <hi>Stawel,</hi> and ſo procured his liberty. And ſhortly after, the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> ſent to this Informant for Twenty pounds as his part of Two thouſand pounds; which the Meſſenger that came to him from the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> told him, was to be ſent to the Gariſon of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> then held for the late King; which Meſſenger alſo told this Informant (as from the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi>) That in caſe the Money was not forthwith paid, he the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> would ſend this Informant to the <hi>Bridewel</hi> in <hi>Taunton;</hi> and would there keep him a priſoner, until he had paid full Two hundred pounds, to which his Fine was increaſed.</p>
                  <p>And he further ſaith, That the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> continued Governor of <hi>Taunton</hi> about one year; during which time, divers well affected perſons to the Parliament, were by his command made priſoners, and put to fine, and ranſom for their affection to the Parliament: As namely, Mr. <hi>Evans</hi> the School Maſter, Mr. <hi>Iaſper Chaplin,</hi> then Major of <hi>Taunton,</hi> Mr. <hi>George Powel,</hi> one of the Juſtices of the Peace for the Town, with divers others: And that during Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> Government there, divers of the Parliament Officers and Soldiers were brought in there, and made priſoners, and there kept by his Command, until ſuch time as they were diſcharged by Exchange, or let go upon their Parol.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Iohn Adams.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <head>
                           <hi>October 22. 1650.</hi> Examinations taken upon Oath the day and year above written, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Directions from the Right Honorable <hi>The High Court of Juſtice,</hi> concerning certain High Crimes and Miſdemeanors commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Sir <hi>John Stawel,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> for levying War againſt the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>GEorge Treagel</hi> of <hi>Taunton,</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> Clothier, Aged Fifty years, or thereabouts, ſworn and examined, ſaith, That he hath known Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> for the ſpace of Twenty years, or thereabouts; and that he knew that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſeven years ſince, the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> was Governor of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119492:9"/>
Town of <hi>Taunton,</hi> for the late King againſt the Parliament: And that the ſaid Sir <hi>John,</hi> together with other of the Kings Party, committed this Deponent as a priſoner into the Caſtle of <hi>Taunton,</hi> for the ſpace of five weeks, or thereabouts, for his affection to the ſtate: Part of which time he was kept in Irons. And further ſaith, That the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> did raiſe Forces both of Horſe and Foot for the late King, and levied War againſt the Parliament. And alſo ſaith, That he was fined by the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi> in the ſum of Forty pounds, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of upon the payment of Fifteen pounds he fled away.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>George Treagel.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander Kingſland</hi> did then likewiſe depoſe to this effect, That <hi>Anno</hi> 1643. Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> was Governor of <hi>Taunton</hi> for the King, and did impriſon this Deponent, and divers other well-affected; and kept them in Irons, until they had paid great ſums for their enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Dunſcomb</hi> did then likewiſe ſwear to this effect, That Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi> committed him to <hi>Ilcheſter</hi> Goal, to lie there till he did rot, if he would not take up Arms againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Robert Audrey</hi> alſo upon his Oath, did affirm to this effect, That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> being Governor of <hi>Taunton,</hi> this Deponent for his affection to the Parliament was indicted for High Treaſon at <hi>Wells;</hi> and Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi> ſaid, That he would ſee this Deponent hanged, drawn and quartered, for being againſt the King; and would hang his quarters upon the Gates of <hi>Taunton.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <head>Some Particulars of the <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> of Sir <hi>John Stawel,</hi> Knight; Anſwered by <hi>Chriſtopher Taylor,</hi> the now Major of <hi>Taunton, November 28. 1653.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>NOtwithſtanding the fair gloſs that Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vored by his <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> to put upon the cruel dealings with many of the Inhabitants of this Town, which were well affected to the Parliament, I do certifie as followeth, That where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> ſets forth that there were Eight thouſand pounds impoſed on this Town, in the pain of a Fine to prevent plundering, and his fair dealing with the Inhabitants thereof, as he was their Governor, I do certifie, That there were great plunders committed by his Party here. And for my own part, I was put unto Three hundred pound Fine, whereof I paid One hundred and fifty pound; and for Fifty pound of it, was inforced to engage my <hi>Taunton-Dean</hi> Land Before the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of which One hundred and fifty pounds, I was often threatned with impriſonment, if I did not pay it according to his Order. And that on the payment of my laſt Fifty pound, I being much unprovided
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119492:10"/>
at that time, I deſired him, that he would accept of Twenty pounds parcel thereof, for that time, and that the payment of Thirty pound reſidue, might be reſpited until the Thurſday following, which he would not admit of; but by his command, I ſtood committed, for ſome time, and longer had continued in cuſtody, had not Mr. <hi>John Syms</hi> engaged to ſee it paid. And afterwards, beſides the extorting of the ſaid One hundred and fifty pound from me, he commanded a houſe of mine to be pulled down near the Caſtle-gate, which I had not long before built, and erected; and at this time (if it ſtood) would have yeelded Ten pound by the year. And as if the pulling it down had not been enough, he would not ſuffer me (though my Wife importuned him thereunto) to ſave the Tyle-ſtones, which by computation were worth about Ten pound; but telling her he had nothing elſe to imploy his Soldiers about. So they beat them down, and ſpoiled them, and carried away the whole ſtones, being about One hundred loads.</p>
                        <p>And Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> having, during his Government, commanded the Faſt (appointed to be kept Wedneſdays) to be kept Fridays, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation on Sabbath-days and Faſting-days being very thin, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the inability and diſaffection of the Miniſter which Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> aſſigned here to Preach; required two of the Company to go into every Street of the ſaid Town, and learn who reſorted to other places to hear the Word Preached. Whereupon Sir <hi>John</hi> once having had intelligence of many Women that went to other Congregations, he ſaid in my hearing, That he would appoint a Party of Soldiers to meet them, who ſhould ſtrip them to their Smocks, and that, that act ſhould not be taken as done by the Soldiers, but by himſelf.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <head>To ſet forth in part the cruel dealings of Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi> towards us the Inhabitants of the Town of <hi>Taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> in the time of the late Wars, I <hi>Matthew Quaſh</hi> of <hi>Taunton,</hi> do certifie as followeth.</head>
                        <p>AT the coming in of the Kings Army into our Town of <hi>Taunton</hi> aforeſaid, I had no ſooner put off my Arms, but was extremely plundered, and my two Sons taken priſoners; and for one of them I muſt pay Twenty pound for his ranſom, or elſe he muſt be hanged (Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> being then Governor of this Town.) In a few days after, there was a Fine of Eight thouſand pounds impoſed on us the ſaid Inhabitants; and thereupon, my ſelf and others were called up together in the Market-place, by the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, where they demanded of us our Fines, which were very hard for us in our plundered condition; and on our refuſal of payment thereof, I and the reſt were preſently committed by Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> unto the Caſtle, where I was kept for the ſix firſt days without any bit of Victuals, unleſs I would come to their Ordinary of Fourteen ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings a week, which was too hard for me. And indeed, I was loath to ſtrengthen then againſt my Friends, by any ſupply of money, as they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119492:10"/>
deſired; but my neceſſity compelled me to Petition to have ſuch pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, as I could, of my own, or to have a Joyner to make me a Coffin: For in ſuch a condition I could not long ſubſiſt; And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon liberty was granted me to have Victuals of my own. In a few weeks after this, we were removed from the Caſtle, and committed priſoners to the <hi>Bridewel,</hi> by Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel;</hi> he ſaying (though our impriſonment was ſo grievous) That whilſt theſe Townſmen have ſo much eaſe in the Caſtle, they will not go from their money. And in the ſaid <hi>Bridewel,</hi> we were kept in Irons night and day, for a long while. Mr. <hi>William Mills</hi> now in <hi>London,</hi> was the man, whoſe Leg was fettered with Irons to my Leg, and he can witneſs it: No Petition could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi> for my enlargement; for he ſaid, That I was the baſeſt Rogue in all the Town, and termed me a Tub-Preacher. But if need require, I could have One thouſand hands for my own, and Childrens faithfulneſs to the Parliament; and that cauſe for which I have ſuffered much loſs in my Eſtate.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Which Teſtimonies fully declare Sir <hi>Johns</hi> diſpoſing of the Eſtates and Perſons of the chiefeſt of thoſe Inhabitants at his will, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all Law: And therefore ſome of them upon their Actions brought againſt him for theſe Injuries, obtained reſpective Verdicts and Judgments upon full Evidence on both ſides, and by Teſtimony ſatisfactory to a Forreign Jury, a Jury at the <hi>Guildhal, London.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were perſons and Eſtates the bounds of Sir <hi>John Stawels</hi> rage: He breathed out threats, and perſecution againſt their Conſciences, ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them Puritans, Tub-Preachers: He fined Mr. <hi>Powel</hi> Ten pound for being abſent from Sir <hi>Johns</hi> Faſts, when ſick: He forbad Mr. <hi>Mills,</hi> and his Fellow-priſoners, either to pray or ſing Pſalms in priſon, telling them, If they did, he would be ſo neer unto them, as to hinder their long Prayers, or to that effect.</p>
            <p>And becauſe many Women reſorted unto other Congregations, and were not willing to hear his Malignant-Preacher, he threatned by his Soldiers to ſtrip them to their Smocks; and would own it as an act of his own. And further his malice extended not to the well-affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Inhabitants of <hi>Taunton</hi> alone, but likewiſe to thoſe of the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor-hood, he ſeized on the Eſtate of Colonel <hi>Ceely,</hi> whilſt he was in the Parliaments ſervice; the incivility of his Soldiers in the mean time haſtning the death of the Colonels Wife, and her childe. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> is pleaſed in his Remonſtrance (<hi>Pag.</hi> 19.) to ſay, That there were taken from the Colonel by his Command, no more then ſeven or eight loads of Hay, in a time of neceſſity. Theſe enſuing Certificates together with a Verdict given for Col. <hi>Ceely</hi> at the <hi>Guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hal, London,</hi> will ſhew the contrary.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="certificate">
                        <p>WHereas Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> in his late Remonſtrance, amongſt many other aggrievances there enumerated, is pleaſed to recompt this one as not the leaſt, <hi>viz.</hi> That Col. <hi>Ceely</hi> hath obtained a Judgment at Law againſt him of One hundred and fifty pound damages, for the carrying away onely of eight loads of Hay, bearing himſelf much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grieved
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119492:11"/>
at the injuſtice of that Tryal and injury done him by the ſaid Colonel.</p>
                        <p>Let the Impartial reade, and then judge of the Cauſe.</p>
                        <div type="part">
                           <p>It will be ſufficiently proved by Teſtimony of divers (beſides the Warrants under his own hand) that a Party of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> Horſe plundred the Houſe of all his Goods and Houſhold-ſtuff, carried away divers of his Writings, and Living goods: That the Hay of Sixty Acres, and Two hundred pounds worth of Corn, growing on the Farm at <hi>Charlton,</hi> was carried away and ſeiſed on: So as his Wife was denied two Pecks a week for her ſelf and children. That one <hi>Walton</hi> his Captain, by his command, with Troopers, entred the Houſe and Chamber with Piſtols and Swords drawn, where Col. <hi>Ceely</hi> his Wife was with her Midwife, and put her in ſuch fear, that ſoon after ſhe died of a Convulſion, then contracted, and her childe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
                           <p>Now if the Colonel received no more damage then the loſs of eight loads of Hay, let all men judge.</p>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>It is therefore wondred, That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> ſhould paſs by ſo ſlightly the ſufferings of thoſe who felt his unjuſt plunder and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and yet bear the damage thereof legally obtained ſo heavily (though little in conſideration to the wrong done, and yet unpaid.) And in a Remonſtrance (ſet out to gain pity (as it is ſuppoſed) by a Miſ-narative of his own ſufferings) ſhould uſe ſo little truth and ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Relation of the loſs of another man.</p>
            <p>This is inſerted, to undeceive the people, and take off the ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of a legal Tryal had and proſecuted.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <p>WHereas Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bathe,</hi> in a late Pamphlet of his, intituled, <hi>His Remonſtrance,</hi> and in the 19 <hi>Page</hi> there, hath averred, That onely ſeven or eight load of Hay on Col. <hi>Ceelyes</hi> Eſtate were taken away by his command. I <hi>William Ceely</hi> of the <hi>Middle-Temple, London,</hi> Eſquire, do hereby certifie to all whom it ſhall concern, That I did in or about the year of our Lord God, 1643. or 1644. cauſe to be carried from the Lands of the ſaid Colonel, to my Houſe at <hi>Huntham,</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> of the Hay of the ſaid Colonel, to the number of fifty ſix loads, or near thereabouts. All which Hay (about ten loads onely excepted) was by ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables of thoſe parts, and by colour of ſeveral Warrants under the proper hand-writing of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> (which I then ſaw, and well knew) taken away; and that the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> did juſtifie the taking away thereof, uttering theſe or the like words unto me, Your Brother (meaning the ſaid Colonel) is a Traytor, and therefore I will have his Hay. And that afterwards my ſelf being Subpena'd to give my Teſtimony in a Cauſe, then to be tryed at the <hi>Guildhal, Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> between the ſaid Colonel and Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> for taking away the ſaid Hay, I did appear and gave my Teſtimony to the effect aforeſaid; and that there were produced at that tryal by the ſaid Colonel, three
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119492:11"/>
other Witneſſes beſides my ſelf, <hi>viZ. Henry Hammond, Tho. Bridge,</hi> and <hi>William Chaple,</hi> whoſe teſtimony was as touching the taking away of that Hay, agreeing with mine in effect.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <dateline>Given under my hand <date>this firſt day of <hi>November</hi> 1654.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Henry Ceely</hi> of <hi>Northcurry,</hi> was likewiſe plundred and impriſoned, and Mr. <hi>Henry Myntern</hi> impriſoned by Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> but wherefore, and in what manner, their own Depoſitions hereunder tranſcribed will beſt declare.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <head>
                           <hi>November 23, 1650.</hi> The Information of Captain <hi>Henry Mintern</hi> of <hi>Cheſſelborough</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> taken before Sir <hi>John Thorowgood</hi> Knight, <hi>Iohn Hurſt,</hi> and <hi>William Weſton, Eſquires,</hi> a Committee of the High Court of Juſtice for Examination.</head>
                        <p>THis Informant ſaith, That being an Officer in Arms for the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, he was taken Priſoner at <hi>Glaſtonbury</hi> about St. <hi>James</hi>'s day, in the year 1643. and brought before Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> then Governor of <hi>Taunton</hi> and after ſome examination of him concerning the eſtate of our Army; the ſaid <hi>Stawell</hi> by order committed this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant to the Caſtle of <hi>Taunton,</hi> where he remained about ſix months, and from thence by the order of the ſaid <hi>Stawell,</hi> was carried by twelve Dragoons to the common Gaol at <hi>Ivelcheſter,</hi> being carried in diſgrace through three Market Towns in his paſſage to the ſaid Gaol. And this Informant ſaith, that being a priſoner in <hi>Taunton</hi> Caſtle aforeſaid, after four daies impriſonment, this Informant, and divers others were brought before a Councel of War at the place where the Aſſizes are uſually kept in <hi>Taunton,</hi> where <hi>Stawell</hi> ſate as Governor of the Town, and Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the ſaid Councel, where after examination this Informant was ſent back to the Caſtle where he remained untill the Aſſizes held at <hi>Wels</hi> about three weeks or a month before <hi>Chriſtmas An.</hi> 1643. and was there Indicted for high Treaſon, and examined by Mr. <hi>Richard Newcourt,</hi> then Clerk to Sir <hi>John Stawell;</hi> and the day after he was brought before Sir <hi>John</hi> Stawell at Mr. <hi>Waldrons</hi> houſe in <hi>Wels</hi> where his ſaid Examination was read to him, and Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> forced this Informant to ſubſcribe the ſame, and refuſed to take Bail for this Informant, although 1000 <hi>l.</hi> bail was offered. And Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> further told this Informant, he was a Rebel and a Traitor, and ſhould be tryed for his life; after which he was remaunded back to priſon untill he was relieved by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Forces.</p>
                        <p>This Informant further ſaith, that being of the Grand Iury in the year 1647. one <hi>Richard Cluff</hi> of <hi>Taunton</hi> (ſince deceaſed) came before this Informant and divers others of the Grand Iury, and informed them that there was means made to Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> for the reprieval of one <hi>Vicca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> a ſouldier of Captain <hi>Clarks,</hi> in the year 1643. or thereabouts, at which time the ſaid <hi>Viccary</hi> was condemned by a Councel of War in <hi>Taunton,</hi> and executed before the window where Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> was
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119492:12"/>
to ſup; and the ſaid <hi>Cluff</hi> ſaid further to the ſaid Grand Iury, that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> refuſed to reprieve him, and bid the Executioner do his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: and accordingly he the ſaid <hi>Viccary</hi> was executed.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Henry Mintern.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <head>
                           <hi>October 22. 1650.</hi> Examinations taken upon Oath the day and year above written, by vertue of Directions from the right Honourable the High Court of Iuſtice, concerning certain high crimes and miſdemeanors committed by Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> for Leavying War againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>HEnry Ceely</hi> of North-<hi>Curry</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, aged 53 years or thereabouts, ſworn and examined, ſaith, That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> and Governor of <hi>Taunton</hi> in the year 1643, or 1644. about the firſt of <hi>February,</hi> ſent a Troop of horſe to the houſe of the ſaid <hi>Ceely</hi> by night, by one Captain <hi>Walton,</hi> and plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred the houſe of the ſaid <hi>Ceely,</hi> and carried him away priſoner to <hi>Taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and there kept him in cruel endurance ſo long as the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> ſtaid there Governor, threatning him with hanging and death for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to the Parliament, and at his, the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> departure from <hi>Taunton,</hi> ſent the ſaid <hi>Ceely</hi> to the priſon of <hi>Bridgewater,</hi> then in the power of the late King, to the undoing of him the ſaid <hi>Ceely</hi> and his Family. Alſo in the time of this Deponents impriſonment in <hi>Taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> did cauſe to be hanged and put to death, one <hi>Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carie,</hi> for refuſing to go in Arms againſt a Town in the County of <hi>Dor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet,</hi> named <hi>Lyme-Regit.</hi> And further ſaith, That the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> did appear with many more in Arms in the County aforeſaid at <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhals Elme,</hi> to the intent and purpoſe to wound, kill, and ſlay thoſe that adhered to the Parliament, as he the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> confeſſed to this Depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent when he was in priſon in <hi>Taunton</hi> aforeſaid, and ſaid, that all thoſe that were at <hi>Marſhals Elme,</hi> deſerved to be hanged as Traitors, for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to the Parliament. And this Deponent doth verily believe that the bloud ſhed at <hi>Marſhals Elme,</hi> was the firſt bloud ſhed in the Weſt of <hi>England.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <div type="part">
                           <p>I <hi>Iohn Baker</hi> of <hi>Higham</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> Eſquire, do hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly certifie the unchriſtian dealings of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> towards me, who having received a wound and maim at <hi>Launſdown</hi> fight (whereof I lay dangerouſly ſick a long time) as ſoon as Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> underſtood that there were hopes of life, granted his Warrant for the apprehending of me and my brother, threatning that if he took us, he would hang us. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, his Tyranny was ſuch, that we could expect no other, had not God preſerved us out of his hands and fury, by letting of us have private no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of his deſigne; upon which this Certificants friends conveyed me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by night, and hid me in ſeveral places to avoid his rage.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Iohn Barker.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </div>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119492:12"/>Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> did alſo commit Mr. <hi>Martyn Sandford,</hi> the then High-Sheriff of the County of <hi>Somerſet</hi> to the Priſon of the Bridewell for ſome actings of the Sheriff for the advantage of the Parliament; which, as it is thought, ſhortned his aged daies. And to compleat his cruelty, he cauſed to be hanged one <hi>Chriſtopher Viccary,</hi> for refuſing to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament and the dictates of his conſcience, as appears by the precedent and following Depoſitions.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <head>
                           <hi>October 22. 1650.</hi> Examinations taken upon Oath, the day and year above written, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Directions from the right Honourable the High Court of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, concerning certain high Crimes and miſdemeanours committed by Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> for Leavying War againſt the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>GEorge Lyſſant</hi> of <hi>Taunton</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> Woollen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draper, aged forty years or thereabouts, ſworn and examined, ſaith, That he knew Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to be late Governor of <hi>Taunton,</hi> and that he in that time did raiſe Forces for the late King, both of horſe and foot againſt the Parliament, and that the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> did raiſe, and went with Forces from <hi>Taunton</hi> againſt the Town of <hi>Lyme,</hi> and that the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> together with others of the Kings party, did fine the ſaid Town of <hi>Taunton</hi> for their Rebellion againſt the late King, in the ſum of 8000 <hi>l.</hi> for that they did adhere unto the Parliament. And further ſaith, that he ſaw one <hi>Reeves</hi> Major unto the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> (upon the clamors and outcries of the people of the ſaid Town) to goe into the Quarters of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> to ſeek to ſave the life of a Souldier, whoſe name was reported to be <hi>Chriſtopher Viccary,</hi> who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly lived at <hi>Norton,</hi> which ſaid <hi>Reeves</hi> returning back again, ſaid he could not prevail, but that the ſaid <hi>Viccary</hi> muſt ſuffer; whereupon im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after the ſaid <hi>Viccary</hi> was hanged. And alſo ſaith, that he, this Deponent, was by the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> fined in the ſum of 100 <hi>l.</hi> for his affection to the Parliament, the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaying, that this Deponent was a Rebel againſt the King.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>VVIlliam Savage</hi> of <hi>Taunton</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> Lock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith, aged fifty years, or thereabouts, ſworn and examined, ſaith, That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> was about ſeven years ſince Governor of the Town of <hi>Taunton</hi> for the late King, againſt the Parliament. And alſo ſaith, that one <hi>Chriſtopher Viccary,</hi> who ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times quartered in this Deponents houſe, being then a Souldier under the command of Captain <hi>Robert Clark</hi> in the late Kings ſervice, was by one Maior <hi>Reeves,</hi> after he was condemned to ſuffer death, carried into the Caſtle of <hi>Taunton,</hi> and immediately after brought forth again, and hanged by the order and appointment of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Viccary</hi> being drunk at the time of his ſuffering. And further
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119492:13"/>
ſaith, That the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> committed this Deponent unto Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for his affection to the Parliament, and there detained him for the ſpace of three or four daies.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>George Deacon</hi> of the Pariſh of <hi>Norton-fitZ-Warren</hi> in the Coutty of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> Husbandman, aged 28 years, or thereabouts, ſworn and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, ſaith, That he knew Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to be Governor of the Town of <hi>Taunton</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet</hi> for the late King againſt the Parliament, in the years 1643, or 1644. And that the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> did raiſe Forces both of foot and horſe for the late King againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And further ſaith, that he doth well remember one <hi>Chriſtopher Viccary</hi> of <hi>Norton</hi> aforeſaid, who was then a Souldier under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Captain <hi>Robert Clark</hi> for the Kings ſervice; which ſaid <hi>Viccary</hi> being by the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> and others, commanded to march from <hi>Taunton</hi> unto and againſt <hi>Lyme,</hi> which he the ſaid <hi>Viccary</hi> refuſing, was by one Major <hi>Reeve</hi> carried into the Caſtle of <hi>Taunton,</hi> and condemned to ſuffer death; which ſaid <hi>Reeves</hi> upon the outcries of the people of the ſaid Town, went unto the then Quarters of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> to ſeek to ſave the life of the ſaid Souldier; which ſaid <hi>Reeves</hi> returning back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, ſaid, he could not prevail, but that he, the ſaid <hi>Viccary,</hi> muſt ſuffer; who imediately after was hanged on a Gibbet in the Market place of <hi>Taunton,</hi> by the order and appointment of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> as this Deponent verily believeth, he, this Deponent being then a ſervant unto the ſaid Captain <hi>Robert Clark.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Henry Weſt</hi> of <hi>Taunton</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> aged 42 years, or thereabouts, ſworn and examined, ſaith, That Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> in the years 1643, or 1644. was Governor of the Town of <hi>Taunton</hi> aforeſaid for the late King, againſt the Parliament, and that he raiſed Forces both of horſe and foot for the ſaid late King againſt the Parliament. And this Examinant further ſaith, that he being a Captain for the Parliament, at and before the time of the enemies entrie into the ſaid Town. The ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> impoſed on this Deponent a fine of 500 <hi>l.</hi> whereof he paid the ſumm of 250 <hi>l.</hi> in money and goods. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, that he knew there was a Souldier whoſe name he doth not now well remember, who was commanded with others to march from <hi>Taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> unto and againſt <hi>Lyme,</hi> who marching a little beyond this Deponents houſe in Silverſtreet, did there firſt lay down his Arms, for which he was carried away, and afterwards hanged.</p>
                        <p>He further ſaith, that one Mr. <hi>Anthony Pardee,</hi> late Miniſter of the ſaid Town, told this Deponent, that the Lady <hi>Stawell</hi> did pitch down on her knees unto the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> her husband, craving of him to ſave the ſaid ſouldiers life, who in wrath denied her, and took her by the arm and thruſt her forth of dores; which ſaid Lady after employed the ſaid <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee</hi> to ſue for the ſaid ſouldiers pardon, who upon his motion was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to hold his peace. And after this Examinant ſaw the ſaid ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier hanged.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Philip Atherton</hi> of <hi>Hillforrence</hi> in the County of <hi>Somerſet</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſworn and examined, ſaith, That he was Enſigne unto Captain <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119492:13"/>
Clark,</hi> in the time when Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> was Governor of the Town and Caſtle of <hi>Taunton</hi> for the late King againſt the Parliament, and was in the ſaid Town when one <hi>Vicarry,</hi> a ſouldier to the ſaid Captain <hi>Robert Clark</hi> was condemned to ſuffer death by a Councel of War (as this Deponent conceiveth) who was then perſonally preſent, and heard the Debate of the ſaid Councel of War, and the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death given by the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> in theſe words, That the ſaid <hi>Viccary</hi> ſhould go from thence to the Caſtle of <hi>Taunton,</hi> and from thence to the Cornhill, and there to be hanged untill he was dead, or words to the like effect.</p>
                        <p>And further ſaith, that about four or five hours after of the ſame day, he, this Deponent, ſaw the ſaid <hi>Viccary</hi> brought forth and hanged accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the order and appointment of the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> notwithſtanding there were ſeveral means uſed by ſolicitation to the ſaid ſir <hi>Iohn,</hi> by one Major <hi>Reeves,</hi> to ſave the ſaid <hi>Viccary's</hi> life: And further ſaith, That when the ſaid <hi>Viccary</hi> was commanded to march by the ſaid ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> from <hi>Taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> unto and againſt <hi>Lyme</hi> (he, this Deponent verily believeth) the ſaid <hi>Viccary</hi> was diſtempered with drink.</p>
                        <p>By which Depoſitions it is evident, that <hi>Chriſtopher Viccary</hi> (when he was drunk) was hanged by Sir <hi>John Stawels</hi> command, for refuſing to march (as formerly he had refuſed) againſt the Parliament Gariſon at <hi>Lyme,</hi> notwithſtanding the importunate intreaties of the Lady <hi>Stawell</hi> (his own wife) Mr. <hi>Pardee</hi> a Miniſter, and Major <hi>Reeves</hi> (his own Major) to the contrary; which refuſal, although Sir <hi>John</hi> endeavoureth to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe by the aſperſion of Mutiny, ſometimes for pay, or advance money, and afterwards for want of Arms; yet in truth it was to ſatisfie the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of his conſcience; for if want of pay and arms had been the cauſe of his pretended mutiny, the pay being ſatisfied, and the arms delivered to ſatisfaction (as Sir <hi>John</hi> confeſſeth they were) he would readily have marched; but he refuſed notwithſtanding, and ſwore he would not go; ſo as the pay and the arms were but pretences; the conſcience was the cauſe of the refuſal: neither could this refuſal be a mutiny within the Kings Military Articles, for Sir <hi>John</hi> (as himſelf confeſſeth) receiving Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from the late King to ſend a hundred men to the ſiege of <hi>Lyme,</hi> ſends for an ancient Trained Band, under the command of Captain <hi>Robert Clark</hi> (whereof <hi>Viccary</hi> was one) in order to ſend them to <hi>Lyme;</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was not formerly liſted in that ſervice, he now refuſed to march, and therefore was hanged; but by what Law or Juſtice he was either thus hanged, or a mutinier; let each man judge. Where are now thoſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious expreſſions of Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> in his Remonſtrance; that he acted not beyond the moderate and ſober limitations of a contrariant; that he was a lover of his Country, and a protector of every man in his property; that he was governed in all the courſe of his life, by that divine rule and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal in humanity; do, as you would be done unto: Hath not every one of theſe his acts exceeded the ſober limitations of a Contrariant? can this man be ſaid to be a lover of his Country, when he ſought the deſtruction of the faithful thereof? or a protector of property, when each action of his intrenched on it? were not undeſerved Impriſonment, Irons, Chaines, ſwolne Legs, pinching hunger, weakened bodies, and exaction of monies thereby, ſcandalous language, perſecuted conſciences, threats of death,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119492:14"/>
and death it ſelf the emblems of his love and moderation, and ſo proved? and by many more ready to be proved and certified. And yet this man dares to Remonſtrance, would Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> have been done unto, as he hath done unto others? certainly no, his frequent complaints of his late condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (though deſerved) do witneſs the contrary.</p>
                        <p>Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> at length concludes his Government at <hi>Taunton</hi> with an act of humanity, ſhewn to Miſtreſs <hi>Treagle,</hi> touching Sir <hi>Samuel Roll</hi> his Eſtate; which (as he ſuppoſeth) did put an end to that his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. But whatſoever his civilities were to the Wife, he was very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civil to the Husband, as his own Depoſitions doth evidence. And as one or two bad acts do not make a good man bad, ſo one or two good actions make not a bad man good; nor in any ſort excuſe or diminiſh his wickedneſs.</p>
                        <p>And it hath been obſerved, That wicked men have ſometimes ruined themſelves in not being wicked enough, through a deſire to be honeſt themſelves. If Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> had taken away this Plate, as he did the Goods of many others, and which he might have as juſtly, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps he had continued longer in his Command; but doing not the one, he loſt the other, by the injuſtice of his friends, not the ſword of an enemy.</p>
                        <p>But now the Scene is altered, and Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> that formerly ſate at <hi>Taun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> triumphing over the lives and liberties of the well effected there, is now beſiedged in <hi>Exon,</hi> by the Parliaments forces, and enforced in order to his ſafety to Article with them for his life and liberty; and had been by reaſon of his high crimes aforeſaid denied, if he had been known in that City; but lying there privately, and being compriſed within the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral words of thoſe Articles; the then General, Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> gave him the paſs mentioned in his <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> pag. 22. In which paſs, (grounded on the 22 Article) it is obſervable, that Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> had the free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of his perſon and perſonal eſtate, during the ſpace of four Moneths next after the ninth of <hi>April</hi> 1646. to make his compoſition with the Parliament, and if he could not make any ſuch compoſition, then within the ſaid four Moneths, he was to depart the Kingdome, if he though ſit, or otherwiſe to ſtay in the Kingdome, but not in the quarters of the Parliament, but in ſome of the Kings Garriſons, (there being then divers of them not reduced;) for certainly, it was never the intention of thoſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, that Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> having made no Compoſition, ſhould notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the four Months continue in thoſe quarters with freedome of perſon. The words of the twelfth Article (which compoſition being made, they ſhall have indempnity of their perſons and enjoy their eſtates) do import ſo much. This being the ſcope of thoſe Articles and Paſs, the queſtion will ſolely be, whether Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> by any neglect or act of his ſince that rendition, hath ſo forfeited either by breach or not performance of thoſe Articles (for both are alike penal unto him) as that the benefit of thoſe Articles being by him thereby loſt, the Parliament might juſtly for his offences, deprive him both of life, liberty, and eſtate, his pardon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conditional, ſo as he perform, what on his part, by theſe Articles ought to be performed.</p>
                        <p>Now that Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> hath of ſet purpoſe, and wilfully neglected the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119492:14"/>
performace of his part of theſe Articles, and thereby forfeited the ſame, will evidently appear if it be premiſed; neither can it be denied, but that Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> hath not as yet actually made his Compoſition with the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, neither did he ſubmit unto, or endeavour it from the 14 of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril</hi> 1646. (when he obtained the Generals paſs) unto the 18 of <hi>Iuly</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing (being the day he ſubſcribed before the Committe of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia of the City of <hi>London,</hi> according to the order of the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of the 2 of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1646) there being in that interval of time above thirteen weeks, and ſo much of the four Moneths limited for his Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſpent by his ſole neglect: and yet ſuch his ſubſcription was no ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to Compoſition, without the 12 of thoſe Articles, but a prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative thereunto only.</p>
                        <p>Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> informeth us in his <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> Page 22. that Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> having the next day after Sir <hi>Iohn</hi>'s coming to <hi>London</hi> (which he ſaith, was on the 15 of July given him a friendly viſit (as he then underſtood) Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> did a day or two before he preſented his Petition to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Goldſmiths Hall, wait upon Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> at his brothers houſe in Fanchurch-ſtreet, and did acquaint him of his purpoſe to Petition, and prayed his furtherance therein. It was indeed a friendly viſit of Mr. <hi>Aſhe,</hi> and for Sir <hi>Johns</hi> good, if he would ſo have underſtood it; for Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> confeſſeth, that Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> did thereupon acquaint him with the day that the Committee ſate, at which time Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> did promiſe not to fail to be there himſelf, and would in all friendly manner further his buſineſs. But Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> doth not tell us, That Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> did at the time of his viſit, acquaint him, that he marvelled why Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> ſtaid ſo long in the Country, ſeeing his time for compounding was almoſt expired, and wiſhed him forthwith to come unto <hi>Goldſmiths Hall.</hi> And that at the time when Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> came to Mr. <hi>Aſhe,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> deſired him to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him with the manner of their proceedings there; which Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> did, together with the form of Petitions uſually preſented, and wherein either a delinquency, or ſome act equivalent muſt be expreſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> muſt bring in a particular of his Eſtate. Which friendly advice of Mr. <hi>Aſh,</hi> if Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> had followed, he had long ſince reſted under the peace of thoſe Articles: But Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> wilfully neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both the time and manner of his Petitioning.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>For the time, it appeareth, both by the Two and twentieth of thoſe Articles, which is the Article of Explanation, and the Generals Paſs, That ſuch perſons as were compriſed within thoſe Articles, were to make their Compoſition within four moneths from the ninth of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pril,</hi> 1646. Which moneths being underſtood to conſiſt of Eight and twenty days to each moneth, expired on the thirtieth day of <hi>Iuly</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, incluſive.</p>
            <p>Now although Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> pretends, that his Petition was delivered on the Four and twentieth day of <hi>Iuly,</hi> five days before the expiration of the four moneths, yet that could not be; for by an Order of that Committee, of the fourth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> following, Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> was ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned to appear on the ſixth, as one that had not then appeared; the words of which Order are,</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="summons">
               <body>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:119492:15"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>Goldſmiths Hall, London. <hi>At the Committee for Compounding,</hi> 
                        <date>Die Martis, 4 Aug. 1646.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>VVHereas by Ordinance of Parliament of the Thirteenth of <hi>November,</hi> there was a Committee appointed to enter the names of all ſuch perſons as ſhould come out of the Enemies Quarters, and to take an accompt of their condition and abode. And by the ſame Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, all ſuch perſons were required to make their appearance before the ſaid Committee accordingly. Now foraſmuch as you have neglected to make your appearance to the ſaid Committee, or to any other Committee of Parliament, notwithſtanding the time allowed by the Articles of <hi>Exon,</hi> upon which you pretend you come in, are expired. Theſe are to require you to attend this Committee, on Thurſday next at four of the clock, there to anſwer your contempt, and give an accompt, what you have done in Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the ſaid Ordinance, or in purſuance of thoſe Articles; and hereof you are not to fail at your peril.</p>
                  <trailer>To Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> Knight.</trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Again, Mr. <hi>Leech,</hi> the Clerk of that Committee did depoſe before the High Court of Juſtice, that he ſaw not Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> there until after the fourth of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> and yet he frequently attended that Committee. Indeed Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſhe</hi> in his Depoſition recited in the Remonſtrance, Page 26. ſaith, That he doth not well remember the preciſe day of the moneth, when Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> firſt appeared before the Committee at <hi>Goldſmiths Hall;</hi> but this he doth well remember, That it was about four days before the four moneths limitted by the Articles of <hi>Exon</hi> expired, which was true, and yet he did not come in until after the fourth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> if Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſhe</hi> be rightly underſtood; for Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> meant <hi>Kalender</hi> moneths, which ended on the tenth of <hi>Auguſt</hi> excluſive; and by this conſtruction, the ſixth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> (the day pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed for his appearance in the Warrant) was four days before the expiration of theſe moneths: And that this was his meaning, doth plainly appear, by the ſubſequent words of his Oath, That when Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> next appeared (and he did but twice appear) before that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, it was about three days after the four moneths limitted by the <hi>Exeter</hi> Articles; For it is granted by all, that his ſecond appearance was on the thirteenth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> for of that date is his <hi>Mittimus,</hi> and the Order likewſe of <hi>Goldſmiths Hall;</hi> for Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> report as appeareth by the Remonſtrance, Page 25. Now the thirteenth day was three days after the tenth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> (the day of the expiration of the <hi>Kalender</hi> moneths) but could not be ſo after the thirtieth day of <hi>Iuly,</hi> the day of the expiration of the four moneths after the rate of eight and twenty days to the moneth; which conſtruction makes the Oath true in every particular, otherwiſe it will prove repugnant to it ſelf. And this doth alſo agree with the Depoſitions of Mr. <hi>Michael Herring,</hi> one other of that Committee, who did ſwear before the High Court of Juſtice, and hath ſince affirmed before the Committee of Parliament, in the <hi>Star-chamber,</hi> That that Committee of <hi>Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths Hall</hi> did not refuſe his pretended Petition; for that he came
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119492:15"/>
not in time, but becauſe he obſerved not the Rules of that Committee; by which Oath, if ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> appeared on the four and twentieth of <hi>Iuly,</hi> he could not be ſaid not to come in time; but if on the ſixth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> then he came not in time, according to the rate of eight and twenty days to the moneth. And although that Committee out of favour to Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> in hopes of his future ſubmiſſion, took no advantage of time; yet ſir <hi>Iohns</hi> coming to Goldſmiths Hall on the ſixth day of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> when his Articles were expired, and that not voluntarily, but by conſtraint, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſummons of that Committee, argues him not very willing to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour his Compoſition, and makes him really guilty of a neglect of performance of his Articles in point of time, he having delayed the time of making his Compoſition, or the leaſt ſubmitting unto it, untill the four moneths expired.</p>
            <p>Again, when Sir <hi>John</hi> did tender his pretended Petition, be it either on the 24 of <hi>July,</hi> and ſo within the four months, as Sir <hi>John</hi> will have it, or after the fourth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> and expiration of them, as that Order of Summons doth evidence, yet could not that Committee receive his Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in regard he had not by that Petition confeſſed his Delinquency, nor expreſſed ſome act of his, amounting unto Delinquency. And although ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> ſeems to complain of Mr. <hi>Aſhe,</hi> for that he refuſed his pretended Petition upon that ground; yet ſir <hi>John</hi> cannot but know that Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> (being then Chairman (as himſelf confeſſeth) did not refuſe it, as contrary to the rules preſcribed that Committee, in his opinion alone, but in the judgement of the whole Committee. And the reaſon why they could not compound with any without ſuch an acknowledgment or expreſſion, was becauſe the Ordinances that did enable this Committee to make Compoſitions, expreſly will, That ſuch perſons with whom this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee ſhould compound, ſhould be Delinquents; for they are therein denominated by the word Delinquents; as doth appear by the ſeveral Orders and Reſolutions of the ſixth of <hi>March</hi> 1644. of the 18 of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 1645. of the fourth of <hi>November</hi> 1645. and the 13 of <hi>December</hi> 1645. and divers others. And ſuch were Delinquents only within the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe reſolutions, as had committed any act for which their Eſtates were liable to Sequeſtration, and no others, though perhaps they had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe offended the Parliament: For this Committee at Goldſmiths Hall had not the abſolute power of compounding, that remained ſtill in the Parliament, but were limited and tyed up to the preſent and future Rules and Orders of the Parliament, in ſuch their compounding with De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents.</p>
            <p>By the Reſolution of the 24 of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1644. of the Houſe of Commons, The Committee at Goldſmiths Hall had power to contract with perſons for the ſale of Lands and Houſes of Delinquents, according to the former Order of the tenth of that moneth of <hi>Iuly,</hi> at eight years purchaſe for Lands at leaſt, and ſix years purchaſe for houſes at leaſt, at the rates they were let at before the wars began.</p>
            <p>By the Reſolution of the fourth of <hi>October</hi> 1645. The Rule by which the Committees ſhall proceed with ſuch as ſhall compound for their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquency, was to be according to the reſpective proportions ſet down in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119492:16"/>
the Propoſitions of both Kingdoms, formerly ſent to His Majeſty for a ſafe and well-grounded Peace.</p>
            <p>By the Reſolution of the Eight of <hi>December,</hi> 1645. ſuch Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents as came to the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> before the firſt of that moneth, were to compound with the Committee at <hi>Goldſmiths Hall</hi> before the firſt of <hi>January</hi> then next.</p>
            <p>The third of <hi>March,</hi> 1644. the Committee of <hi>Goldſmiths Hall,</hi> made their Propoſition to the Houſe of Commons, in theſe words following, That whereas now this Committee doth onely take into conſideration, ſuch Delinquents as come recommended unto them by particular Orders; if this Honorable Houſe ſhall think fit to give this Committee a general power to receive, treat, and compound with whatſoever Delinquents ſhall immediately tender themſelves to this Committee to be compounded with all. They firſt repreſenting unto this Honorable Aſſembly ſuch Compoſitions made, or Fines ſet upon them before any thing be concluded. It will much promote the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Affairs, and have power to ſend for ſuch perſons as they ſhall think to attend that Committee, about their Compoſition and Fine. Whereupon on the ſixth day of <hi>March</hi> following, The Houſe did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, That they aſſented unto this Propoſition and ordered it accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly.</p>
            <p>By the Order of the 23 of <hi>March,</hi> 1645. the Rules for <hi>Goldſmiths Hall</hi> to go by, upon Compoſitions with Delinquents, was to be thoſe Rules that are ſet by the Houſe upon the Propoſitions for ſuch as came in ſithence the firſt of <hi>December.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By which ſeveral Orders and Reſolutions, the Committee at <hi>Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths Hall,</hi> were to compound with Delinquents alone (that word be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely uſed for an expreſſion) and according to certain Rules and Orders, and to conclude with no Delinquent, without certifying the compoſition it ſelf to the houſe.</p>
            <p>This Committee then having power to compound with Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents onely, and Delinquents particularly deſcribed, it was requiſite for that Committee, and it was their conſtant rule, That the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounder ſhould acknowledge either his delinquency, or ſome act done by him, which amounted unto the ſame, to inable them to treat with him; for if a perſon had committed no offence worthy of Sequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and was notwithſtanding ſequeſtred; the Parliament had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed him elſewhere to attend his remedy, and not here: And it was fit, in point of prudence, That ſuch acknowledgement or expreſſion ſhould be in writing, and not by words, or any verbal expreſſion one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to the end, That ſuch writing ſhould remain of Record for the future Indempnity of that Committee, and other the Reaſons of Mr. Juſtice <hi>Lawrence</hi> hereunto annexed: And for theſe Reaſons all ſuch perſons as did here compound, none excepted, were they compriſed within the Articles of <hi>Exon,</hi> or of any other Gariſon, or not within Articles; yet did they Petition in that manner, although they were
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119492:16"/>
as zealous for their King, as Sir <hi>John Stawel,</hi> deeming it wiſdom in them rather ſo to do, then to run the hazard of not performing their Articles, and thereby of the loſs of their Liberty and Eſtate; and eſpecially ſince ſuch acknowledgment or expreſſion, and formality of Addreſs, was within the intention of thoſe Articles: For if a man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth to ſubmit to a Compoſition with theſe Exceptions, certainly he doth agree to ſubmit to all other Rules for ſuch Compoſition, not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly excepted; and this was a conſtant rule, and obſerved at and before the time of the making of thoſe Articles. And therefore in regard Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi> did refuſe to inſert ſuch an Acknowledgment, or Expreſſion in his Petition, he hath in a ſecond particular neglected the performance of his Articles; and that premediately ſince he was preadviſed: Neither is it ſatisfactory, when Sir <hi>John</hi> alleageth, That he did tell Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> he had borne Arms for the late King, and by his command; unleſs for the Reaſons aforeſaid, he had in writing affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as much. And yet this very Paper, or pretended Petition (which was thus delivered) was not preſented by himſelf, but put in by a Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citor: And Sir <hi>John</hi> did refuſe to ſubſcribe the ſame, as Mr. <hi>Michael Herring</hi> hath lately affirmed, before a Committee of this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, ſitting in the <hi>Star-chamber.</hi> And if it ſhall be objected, That although the ſeveral Orders aforeſaid, did inable that Committee to compound onely with Delinquents, it followeth not, They ſhould compound with none but ſuch as <hi>(in terminis)</hi> acknowledged Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quency. It is eaſily anſwered, when it is conſidered, That Sir <hi>John</hi> was not adviſed to acknowledge in expreſs terms, That he was a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent; but if he had in his Petition ſet forth ſome act done by him, amounting to Delinquency, it had been ſufficient; but one of them he was by the conſtant rules of the Committee to inſert in his Petition, which Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> refuſed.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Henry Berkley</hi> (with others) came in upon the Articles of <hi>Exon,</hi> as well as Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> yet Sir <hi>Henries</hi> Petition was in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="petition">
               <body>
                  <head>To the Honorable Committe for Compounding with Delinquents; <hi>The humble Petition of Sir</hi> Henry Berkley, <hi>Knight.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
                  <p>THat your Petitioner as formerly a Commiſſioner of the Army for His Majeſty, and ſince did voluntarily contribute to the Forces raiſed againſt the Parliament, by means whereof, he is become under the notion of a Delinquent. That being in the City of <hi>Exeter</hi> upon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery thereof, humbly craves the benefit of the Articles of the ſame. And that he may be admitted to a favorable Compoſition for his offence, according to the value of his Eſtate, to the end, he may free the ſame from Sequeſtration. And he ſhall pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Subſcribed</hi> Hen. Berkley.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>But Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> having taken on a Reſolution not to compound, took up all pretences to avoid the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:119492:17"/>But Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> asked him, as Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> objecteth, whether he had taken the negative Oath and Covenant, to whom Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> anſwering, no; and that his Articles did free him from taking any Oaths: Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> replyed, that before he could be admitted to Compoſition with them, he muſt take them both. It is anſwered, that there then lay on that Committee a command (ſeveral Ordinances) of both Houſes (the tranſcripts whereof are inſerted) that injoined them to tender that Covenant and negative Oath to all perſons that came to compound, and to ſecure their perſons upon refuſal.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="Parliamentary_order">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Sab. 1 <hi>Nov.</hi> 1645.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>ORdered by the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, That the Committee at Goldſmiths Hall ſhall have power to tender the Solemn League and Covenant to all perſons that come out of the Kings quarters to that Committee to compound, either upon Mr. Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers Paſs or otherwiſe, and to ſecure ſuch as ſhall refuſe to take the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, until they ſhall conform thereunto.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="Parliamentary_order">
                        <head>Sab. 5. April. 1645.</head>
                        <p>BE it ordained by the Lords and Commons in Parliament aſſembled, That all and every perſon of what degree or quality ſoever, that hath lived or ſhall live within the Kings quarters, or been aiding, aſſiſting, or adhearing unto the forces raiſed againſt the Parliament; and hath or ſhall come to inhabite or reſide under the power and protection of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, ſhall ſwear upon the holy Evangeliſts in manner following. I <hi>A. B.</hi> do ſwear from my heart, that I will not directly, nor indirectly adhere unto, or willingly aſſiſt the King in the war; or in this cauſe againſt the Parliament, nor any forces raiſed without the conſent of the two Houſes in this cauſe or war. And I do likewiſe ſwear, that my coming and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting my ſelf under the power and Protection of the Parliament, is without any manner of deſign whatſoever to the prejudice of the proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the two Houſes of Parliament; and without the direction, privity or advice of the King, or any of his Councel or Officers, other then in what I have now made known, ſo help me God, and the contents of this book.</p>
                        <p>And be it ordained by the Authority aforeſaid, that the Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners for the keeping of the great Seal of <hi>England</hi> for the time being, ſhall have power, &amp; are hereby authoriſed to tender &amp; adminiſter the ſaid Oath, unto any Peer, or Wife, or Widdow of any Peer, ſo coming to inhabit as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid. And it ſhall be lawful to, and for the Committee of the Houſe of Commons for Examinations, the Committee for the Militia in <hi>London,</hi> and all Committies of Parliament, in the ſeveral Counties &amp; Cities of the Kingdome, to tender and adminiſter the ſaid Oath unto every other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo coming to inhabite a aboveſaid: &amp; if any perſon not being a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of or aſſiſtant unto, either of the Houſes of the Parliament ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe or neglect to take the ſaid Oath, ſo duely tendered unto him or her,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119492:17"/>
as aboveſaid; the ſaid Commiſſioners and Committees reſpectively ſhall and may commit the ſame perſon to ſome priſon, there to remain without bail or mainprize, untill he ſhall conform thereunto.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>It is true that the Articles of <hi>Exon,</hi> do free all perſons compriſed therein, from all Oaths, Covenants, and Proteſtations: but it is likewiſe as true, that thoſe Articles were not at the time of Sir <hi>Iohn</hi>'s being at Goldſmiths Hall, confirmed by both Houſes, as in right they then ought; indeed the Houſe of Commons had before that time confirmed them, <hi>viZ.</hi> ſixth of May 1646. but they were confirmed by both Houſes not before the fourth of Nov. 1647, above an year after Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> being there; ſo as the command of tendering this Oath and Covenant lay ſtill upon that Committee, and they were not to compound with any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, be he within Articles or without, before he had taken them; and therefore it was no injuſtice in that Committee to deny Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> to treat with him before he was ſworn, for they were prohibited otherwiſe to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him to Compoſition; which Sir <hi>Anthony Irbie</hi> in his Letter (men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the Remonſtrance page 60) is pleaſed to confeſs, <hi>viZ.</hi> that the truth was, that by the order of the Houſe, that Committee was bound up from admitting him to compound, unleſs he took the Covenant, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Houſe would diſpence with it; which (he ſaith) they did, when they approved of thoſe Articles: Certainly when Sir <hi>Anthony</hi> wrote this Letter, he had forgotten that the Negative Oath and Covenant were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to be taken by Compounders, by Ordinances of both Houſes of Parliament. And therefore although the approbation of the Articles of <hi>Exon,</hi> by the Houſe of Commons, ſhould be granted to be a diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe Ordinances in reſpect of them; yet the Ordinance of the Houſe of Lords lay ſtill on that Committee, as a prohibition, not to make any Compoſition without the tendring of thoſe Oaths; otherwiſe why did that Committee (and Sir <hi>Anthony</hi> amongſt the reſt) ſend ſome of thoſe Gent. that were compriſed within thoſe very Articles of <hi>Exon,</hi> to the Houſe of Lords, after that the Houſe of Commons had approved of them to procure ſuch their diſpenſation likewiſe? which had been needleſs, if the approbation of the Houſe of Commons alone had wholly diſengaged that Committee from the tender of thoſe Oaths; and although they were thus limitted, yet was not Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> without his means of Compoſition, for he might have Petitioned the then Parliament, to admit him to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; who did, before the Committee of Goldſmiths Hall were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled conſtantly to compound with Delinquents; which Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or rather refuſing to do, the nonperformance of his Articles lyeth ſtill on his accompt; for ſuppoſe Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> had come to the Court of the Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Bench, or any other Court, and had preſented by Petition his offer to compound with them, and that Court had told him, they could not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound with him; and that thereupon he had ſate down, had not Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> neglected the performance of his Articles, or was it any fault in that Court, that Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> could not be admitted by that Court to compound? certainly no, and there is no difference but that the Court of Upper Bench had no power at all to compound; and the Committee of Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths Hall had ſuch a power, but limited to ſuch rules: which Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> refuſed, the primitive and original power of Compoſition remaining ſtill in the Parliament, which Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> neglected, nay refuſed to ſubmit unto.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:119492:18"/>It is obſervable, that notwithſtanding ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> had denied to take thoſe Oaths, or to acknowledge his Delinquencies; yet that Committee (our of a deſigne to preſerve him) gave him ſome time to conſider thereof (as himſelf confeſſeth, <hi>Remonſtrance pag.</hi> 24.) which he ſeemed to accept (as Mr. <hi>Aſh</hi> affirms) although ſir <hi>John</hi> now denies it. Let it be either; yet it doth aggravate his neglect, or obſtinacy, that having longer time (notwithſtanding the expiration of the four moneths) and finding that Committee was diſabled (otherwiſe) to compound with him, he had not reſorted to the Parliament it ſelf, for his peace. Again, the Houſe of Commons themſelves had after their confirmation of thoſe Articles, and before ſir <hi>John</hi> came to compound, <hi>viZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="Parliamentary_resolution">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Die Martis, 2 Junii 1646.</date>
                           </dateline>
RESOLVED,</opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>THat all perſons that have, or ſhall come and reſide in the Parliament-Quarters, ſhall take the National League and Covenant, and the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Oath, notwithſtanding any Articles that have been, or ſhall be made by the Souldiery.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>So as after this time, the Negative Oath and Covenant were to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by all Compounders, at Goldſmiths Hall, (though they were within Articles) and this by the command of both Houſes. Neither can ſir <hi>John</hi> object the Order following, <hi>viZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="Parliamentary_order">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Die Sabb. October 18 1645.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <hi>ORdered, That all Compoſitions for the diſcharge of the Delinquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of any perſons, and for the taking off their Sequeſtrations, ſhall be made with the Committee of Goldſmiths Hall; and that no other Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee do compound with any Delinquent without the ſpecial directions of this Houſe.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>JOHN BROVVN Cler. Parl.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Nor can ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> upon this Order ſay, that ſince this Order doth enable that Committee to compound with Delinquents in general, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was the only place for ſir <hi>Iohns</hi> addreſs.</p>
            <p>For although they were to compound with all Delinquents yet not untill after the taking of the Oaths; but ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> was to compound without Oaths, which compoſition the Parliament alone could make.</p>
            <p>Again, this Order taketh away this power of compounding, from all other Committees, and centers it in the Committee of Goldſmiths Hall alone; but ſtill reſerving to themſelves, either the power it ſelf in caſes extraordinary, or direction thereof. Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> therefore finding the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Goldſmiths Hall to be limited to Rules and Oaths, from which himſelf pretended an exemption by Articles, ſhould have made his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs to the Parliament to make his Compoſition with them, or from them to receive directions where elſe to make it, eſpecially when the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119492:18"/>
do mention Compoſitions with the Parliament; and ſithence his Compoſition made at Goldſmiths Hall, (if he had made any) muſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it could be effectual, have the approbation of the Parliament.</p>
            <p>If it ſhould be objected, that theſe Articles being confirmed, were become the Articles of the Parliament, and not of the Souldiery; and ſo by conſequence not within the word (Souldiery) in that Order of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of June. It is anſwered, that thoſe Articles ought to have the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of both Houſes; which they having not, until above 12 Months after, they ſtill continued the Articles of the Souldiery; eſpecially when the words are, Articles that have been made by the Souldiery. Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> therefore not making any application to the Parliament, touching the gaining his Compoſition, is guilty of this neglect, thoſe objections not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Naaman</hi> had waſhed twice ſeven times in <hi>Abanah,</hi> or <hi>Pharpar,</hi> he had not been cured; the command, and (together with it) the healing vertue being fixt in Jordan, which <hi>Naaman</hi> upon adviſe wiſely perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was cleanſed of his Leproſie. But Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> not applying himſelf to the Parliament on whom the agreement reſted, and in whom the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding power remained, though importun'd thereunto, continueth yet a Delinquent.</p>
            <p>Every Compounder at Goldſmiths Hall, was to deliver in a particular of his Eſtate, by theſe reſolves following, <hi>viZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="Parliamentary_resolution">
                        <head>Die Sab. 13 <hi>Dec.</hi> 1645.</head>
                        <p>
                           <hi>REſolved, That if any ſhall come in to compound, he ſhall preſent the particular of his Eſtate to the Committee of Goldſmiths Hall, and the true yearly value of it, as it was before theſe troubles began; and for that that is concealed or omitted, he ſhall have no advantage by his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, but ſhall pay four times the yearly value of what real eſtate is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed; and for his perſonal eſtate concealed, he ſhall forfeit all.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Such a particular Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> likewiſe did neglect, both at the firſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond time of his appearance, although adviſed thereunto before he came, by Mr. <hi>Aſhe;</hi> and at his firſt coming by the whole Committee; and it had been wiſdome in Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> to have haſtened his Compoſition, having vainly ſpent already ſo much time thereof: Neither is the objection of weight, that a particular was to be brought in, when the Compounder was admitted to his Compoſition: for Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> was really admitted, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving the Rules of that Committee; whereof a particular was one, and to perform which he had time given him; but at that time neglecting it, his reſolution not to compound appeareth; and without ſuch a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, that Committee being ſtrangers to his eſtate, could not without a ſurvey thereof (which would be chargable to the Commonwealth) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound according to the rates preſcribed them; to avoid which charge, the Parliament ordered a particular.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> having no notice of theſe Rules, hath been vainly objected; for when Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſhe</hi> gave him the viſit, he was informed by him of the form of his Petition and of the particular; and when he firſt came
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119492:19"/>
to Goldſmiths Hall, the Committee gave him longer time (as himſelf confeſſeth) to conſider of the Oath and Covenant; or (as Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſhe</hi> depoſeth) upon hopes that at his next appearance, he would be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter adviſed, and yield ſubmiſſion to the authority of Parliament, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the Rules of the Committee, or (as Mr. <hi>James Aſhe</hi> informeth) to amend his Petition, and bring in his particular to compound, of which alſo he was told by the Committee; neither could it be in any ſort pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to him to ſubſcribe a Delinquency, or ſome act amounting un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it; for this over act of ſubſcription, could not have been treaſon or breach of his Articles, in regard it was known, and taken as an inabling rule of that Committee onely, if it had been, yet the very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription carried with it a pardon of that ſubſcription.</p>
            <p>So as in theſe four particulars, Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> did neglect the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of his Articles; and therefore the blame of his after trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles muſt light on himſelf, not on the Parliament, eſpecially ſince the Committee of Goldſmiths Hall, did admit him to compoſition, accoring to the Rules of Compoſitions, but he would not ſubmit unto it; and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence the Parliament hath performed, what their Armies promiſed in ſuffering Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> quietly to enjoy his liberty, during the four Moneths, and expreſſing their readineſs to compound with him at two years value, had he Petitioned them to that purpoſe, but he wilfully refuſed it; for (as Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> affirmeth) although Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> did appear at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Goldſmiths Hall, yet he never intended to make any Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition there, according to the Order of Parliament, and the rules pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed for Compoſition upon the ſaid Articles, but did oftentimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his reſolution to the contrary; which his reſolution he ſeconded by his carriage and words at his firſt coming thither.</p>
            <p>And although, Sir <hi>Henry Berkly</hi> hath ſaid that it was fitting, and Sir <hi>David Watkins,</hi> that he came to that Committee, with a fair and civil reſpect: And Sir <hi>Anthony Irbie</hi> took no offence with his carriage, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as he thinketh) juſtly there could be any taken, neither ſaw he any incivility at the time he was before them, either in carriage or language: yet hath Mr. <hi>Richard Wareing</hi> depoſed that it was inſolent, Mr. <hi>Michael Herring</hi> that it was very high, Mr. <hi>Samuel Moyer</hi> that his comportment was very inſolent, and Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſhe</hi> that the ſence and ſubſtance of his words were, That the Parliament had ſeized and ſequeſtred his Eſtate, or had taken it away by force, for doing his duty to the King, as by the Law and ſeveral Oaths (which he had taken) he was bound to do; and that he could not have his Eſtate again, unleſs he gave that Committee mony to redeem it: that he was a perſon in debt, and his debt and his debts were much increaſed ſince his Eſtate was taken from him by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by which means he was diſabled to pay the Committee much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, notwithſtanding if they could accept of what he could procure he would then compound with them, for the redemption of his Eſtate.</p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>James Aſhe</hi> doth atteſt that his words were, and Mr. <hi>Samuel Moyer</hi> certifieth, that he ſcornfully ſaid that he was no Delinquent; but the Parliament and they was, who contrary to their Oaths, had fought againſt the King; and although Sir <hi>Henry Berkly</hi> being of the ſame judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and affect, ſo although Sir <hi>David Watkins</hi> by forgetfullneſs or age, and Sir <hi>Anthony Irbie</hi> for ſome other reſpect ſeem now to excuſe him, yet
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119492:19"/>
certainly his deportment then, both in the opinion of Sir <hi>David</hi> and Sir <hi>Anthony</hi> themſelves, was very diſreſpective to the Government, and ſuch, as the whole Committee, and eſpecially Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> being the moſt earneſt, had thereupon reſolved forthwith to have it reported to the Houſe of Commons, had not Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſh</hi> deſired them to give him ſome four or five days reſpite upon the hopes aforeſaid, which the Committee did accordingly.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> having thus voluntarily refuſed the Armies mercy, in not making his Compoſition within the four moneths limited; he was after the expiration of them reduced to a Delinquent that had forfeited his Articles; and therefore cannot complain of injuſtice, when upon his coming to <hi>Goldſmiths-Hall</hi> the 13 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1646. they then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted him for refuſing to take the Negative oath and Covenant; and upon his reiterated miſdemeanors (being higher in his expreſſions then at his firſt being there, although his former expreſſions contemptuouſly diſowned the authority of the Parliament) Ordered Mr. <hi>Stevens</hi> their then Chairman to report ſuch his carriage to the Houſe of Commons. And being thus committed, he did not in the leaſt degree petition or deſire that Committee to be admitted to Compoſition; he only craved maintenance, which that Committee promiſed him to take care of, as himſelf relateth in his <hi>Remonſtrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During his impriſonment there, he and the reſt of the Priſoners (whereof Mr. <hi>Michael Tidcombe,</hi> a Wiltſhire Gentleman, was one) having received an intimation of the late Kings pleaſure, that the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners might make their peace with the Parliament, debated what to do therein, at which debate Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> was preſent: And although the reſt of the Priſoners did agree to make their. Compoſition with the Parliament, yet Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> utterly oppoſed it in his particular, and laughed at ſuch as already had, or would make ſuch Compoſition: which jeering at ſuch Compounders he uſed at another time, by the teſtimony of Mr. <hi>Aſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Afterwards Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> accordingly doth make his Report to the Houſe of Commons, and (as Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſh</hi> hath ſworne before the High Court of Juſtice) to this effect, <hi>viZ.</hi> That the opinion of that Committee was, That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> had ſlighted and contemned the Authority of the preſent Parliament, and forfeited their mercy contained in the Articles of <hi>Exon:</hi> with this concluſion, <hi>That if the Parliament did not make Sir</hi> John Stawell <hi>a Traitor, Sir</hi> John <hi>had made them Traitors.</hi> And this concluſion is likewiſe atteſted by Mr. <hi>Iames Aſh.</hi> Upon which Report Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> is ſent for to the Houſe of Commons: but being ſtaid ſome time in the <hi>Lobby,</hi> till the Debate of the Houſe was ended, Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſh</hi> came unto him and adviſed him to acknowledge his miſcarriage at <hi>Goldſmiths Hall,</hi> crave the pardon of the Houſe, and deſire admiſſion to Compound. Which Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> diſliked, ſaying, That if he were willing, yet he was not able to pay the mony for a Compoſition.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> being brought to the Bar of that Houſe, and refuſing to kneel, is committed to <hi>Newgate</hi> for High-Treaſon for levying war againſt the Parliament; the Tranſcripts of which Order and <hi>Mittimus</hi> are inſerted in the <hi>Remonſtrance, fol.</hi> 29. Where he continued for ſome
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119492:20"/>
years; Neglecting, refuſing, paſſionately diſdaining to Petition to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to a Compoſition, or any way to comply with the Parliament in that behalf, although entreated and importuned thereunto by his wife and friends, that deſired to preſerve him and his Eſtate, and by others that ſtood deeply engaged as Sureties for his Debts.</p>
            <p>His wife hath upon her bared knees, and with many tears, deſired him, if not for her ſake, yet for the ſake of the children of his body (to uſe her words) that he would ſubmit and Petition the Parliament for a Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; which notwithſtanding he ſlighted, as the poor Lady her ſelf, with grief, affirmed to divers Gentlemen of worth; and hath complained of his wilfulneſs, amongſt the reſt, unto Mr. <hi>Iames Aſh,</hi> whoſe teſtimony lately given to the Committee of Parliament, to whom ſir <hi>Iohns</hi> Petition is referred, followeth, <hi>viZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <head>
                           <date>Decemb. 15. 1654.</date> The Information of <hi>James Aſh</hi> 
                           <abbr>Eſq</abbr> (a Member of Parliament) given to the Committee of Parliament to whom the Petition of Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi> is referr'd, in the Caſe of the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawel.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <p>WHo ſaith, That he was preſent at <hi>Goldſmiths-Hall,</hi> when Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> came thither, who delivered a paper which he called a Petition. The Committee, upon receipt and read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that paper, were all of opinion, It was not a Petition to compound. The ſaid Committee thereupon called in Sir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> and asked him ſome queſtions (ſome of them the Informant hath forgot, but theſe he remembers.) Being demanded why he came thither, if not to compound? and they telling him they were a Committee to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound with Delinquents: He ſaid, that he came to have his Eſtate that was taken from him; and did endeavour in his ſpeech to take off the Delinquencie from himſelf, and to caſt it upon the Parliament and Committee. The particular expreſſions he cannot now remember, nor doth he remember the title of the ſaid Petition; but ſaith, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of it was, to have his Eſtate. Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> being withdrawn, the Committee fell into a debate whether his ill carriage there ſhould be reported to the Houſe. But afterwards a Gentleman (Mr. <hi>John Aſh</hi>) moving that he might have three or four dayes to amend his Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition, and bring in a Particular to Compound, (which alſo he was told of by the Committee) He this Informant heard no more of him, till the Report made to the Parliament by Mr. <hi>John Stephens</hi> of his miſcarriage and ill behaviour: which the Parliament highly reſented, and did order him to be ſent for as a Delinquent. Whereupon being brought to the bar of the Parliament, and commanded by the Speaker to kneel; He this Informant ſitting very neer Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> heard him mutter theſe words, <hi>I deſire to know my offence or crime.</hi> Upon which being ordered to withdraw, the Parliament made an Order for his commitment to <hi>Newgate</hi> (as this Informant remembers.) After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119492:20"/>
being by Order of Parliament referred to be tryed for Treaſon, and Report being made to the Parliament of his high carriage, and diſowning their Authority and the Judges that ſate thereby, they were yet more incenſed againſt him. And afterwards, upon the news given to the Parliament of one Mr. <hi>Anthony Aſcams</hi> death, (the Parliament having before declared to bring ſome Delinquents to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment who were excepted from pardon) did refer Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> (amongſt others) to be tryed at the High Court of Juſtice. That during all the Debates when the Parliament gave any Judgment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, conſideration was ſtill had of his Articles; and yet in thoſe Judgments there were hardly any Negatives, but the Queſtion paſſed cleer. That afterwards the Report being made from the High Court of Juſtice, who did not proceed to give ſentence of death againſt him, in regard of the Articles of <hi>Exceter;</hi> many Gentlemen (Members of Parliament in the Houſe) did much wonder thereat; but in regard of the opinion of the ſaid High Court, they did not again refer him to be tryed for his life; but did (as he remembers) <hi>eo inſtanti</hi> paſs a Vote, That his Eſtate ſhould be confiſcate to the Commonwealth: and afterwards paſt the Act for Sale of his Lands. That to this Informants knowledge for many years together, after the firſt apparance of ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> at Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths Hall, there were many endeavours uſed for to have drawn him to compound, and to have had the benefit of his Articles; but he would never be perſwaded thereunto. Now the reaſon of this his knowledg is, becauſe he was privy to the actings on his behalf; and having diſcourſe ſeveral times with the Lady <hi>Stawell</hi> concerning thoſe endeavours which had been uſed to perſwade him to compound: And this Informant ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her, Can there be no way found out whereby he may be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and have the benefit of his Articles? She anſwered this Informant in theſe words, Sir, you know what endeavours have been uſed, and how we would have perſwaded him to have ſuffered his ſon, <hi>Ned Stawell</hi> (meaning him called ſir <hi>Edward Stawell</hi>) to have compounded for his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; but he would not give his conſent thereunto, but did threaten him, if he endeavoured any ſuch thing. For (ſaith ſhe) he doth ſtill flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter himſelf with vain hopes of ſeeing the King reſtored: and although there be every day more unlikelihood then other, yet his faith continues ſtrong.</p>
                        <p>That having ſome diſcourſe with one <hi>Michael Tidcomb</hi> (a Gentleman in <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> as he remembers) upon reading of the Act paſſed by the late little Convention, or Parliament, for the confirmation of the ſale of ſir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> Lands, The ſaid Gentleman ſpake theſe words; I wonder (ſaid he) that ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> ſhould now pretend to the Articles of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceter,</hi> ſince to my knowledge, he did refuſe to have the benefit of them: For (ſaid he) when I was a priſoner in <hi>Ely</hi> Houſe with the ſaid ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> ſome intimation we had from the then King, that we ſhould ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to the Parliament, and compound for our Eſtates. Upon which we had a Debate amongſt our ſelves, and ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> was preſent; and it was the opinion of moſt of them, they ſhould ſubmit to compound; but ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> did declare againſt it, and laughed at them that had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, or did intend it.</p>
                        <p>And this Informant further ſaith, That ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> came to Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119492:21"/>
Hall in the afternoon (as he now remembers) and that this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant was then a Member of Parliament, but not of that Committee: And this Informant ſaith that ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> ſaid theſe words, <hi>I am no Delinquent</hi> (which words he, this Informant remembers poſitively) <hi>but the Parliament and you, who contrary to your Oaths of Allegiance, have fought againſt the King:</hi> Or words to that effect. Being croſs interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> Councel, He ſaith,</p>
                        <p>That it is the cuſtom of the Parliament, when a Delinquent is brought to the Barr, that the Delinquent doe firſt kneel before he receive any Charge: And ſaith that upon the Debates in Parliament it was alleadg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> had forfeited his Articles; and it was clearly the opinion of the Houſe, that he had forfeited his Articles. And that was one ground of their judgement; there was no Vote paſſed to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that he knows of; but it was taken as a thing clear and indiſputable. And further ſaith, That M. <hi>Iohn Aſh</hi> was to have the benefit of ſir <hi>Iohn Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels</hi> Compoſition by Order of the Houſe of the 20 of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1646. (as he takes it) which was to be towards the ſatisfaction of debts and disburſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the value of ten thouſand pounds, which had been entred into by the ſaid Mr. <hi>Aſh,</hi> Col. <hi>Popham,</hi> Col. <hi>Fines, &amp;c.</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> for the ſervice of the Parliament; which being ſatisfied, the overplus was to go to Mr. <hi>Aſh,</hi> towards his loſſes and ſufferings; but for certainty, this Informant refers to the ſaid Order it ſelf.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>This Informant further ſaith, That Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> did report to the Houſe, the high and inſolent behaviour of ſir <hi>John Stawell,</hi> who came to Goldſmiths Hall under the pretence of a Compounder, and had ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken divers words tending to the diſhonour and diſowning of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for which the Committee had committed ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> and commanded him to report the ſame to the Houſe: And he concluded his Report in theſe words;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Although the Parliament ſhall not make ſir</hi> John Stawell <hi>a Traitor, yet he hath made them Traitors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, the Informant ſaith, he doth not know that ever Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſh</hi> did make application to ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> to buy <hi>Aubery,</hi> nor did ever hear of any ſuch thing, untill ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> told the ſtory at the High-Court of Iuſtice, ſix years after the buſineſs of his Compoſition.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="deposition">
               <body>
                  <head>The Information of <hi>Michael Herring</hi> Eſquire, taken the ſame time in the ſame Cauſe,</head>
                  <opener>Who ſaith,</opener>
                  <p>THat he was one of the Committee at Goldſmiths Hall, and preſent when ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> came and preſented himſelf to compound, as he underſtood it; who was very high in his language and in carriage; but this Informant remembers not the words: He refuſed to take the Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Oath and Covenant, and to ſubſcribe his Petition, to acknowledge himſelf a Delinquent, as all men did: For my Eſtate (ſaid he) doe what you will; but I would keep my conſcience to my ſelf. And this Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant refers to his old Examination at the High Court. And further ſaith, That he conceives ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> came to compound, becauſe he
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119492:21"/>
came there and preſented himſelf; but doth not remember that he deſired to compound. There was a Paper preſented, but ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> would not put his hand to it; This Informant did not read it, nor can he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that the Committee read it, nor that they called it a <hi>Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance;</hi> this Informant underſtood it as a Petition, and doth not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the particular reaſon why ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> did not ſubſcribe the Paper, nor did he ſubſcribe any Paper to the Committee, that this Informant knows: And this Informant conceives the ſaid Paper was brought in by ſir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> Sollicitor, who acted for him.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <hi>This is a true Copie,</hi> 
                     <signed>Examined by T. PAUNCEFOOT.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Hitherto ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> notwithſtanding his Impriſonment, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued his reſolution not to compound. It is true, that about five nights after his impriſonment in <hi>Newgate,</hi> he ſent late in the night the Lady <hi>Stawell</hi> to Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſhe,</hi> under pretence of a buſineſs of importance; but when Mr. <hi>Aſh</hi> was come accordingly, he entreated Mr. <hi>Aſh</hi> to move the Houſe for his removal to the Tower for his better accommodation; but being deſired by Mr. <hi>Aſh</hi> to Petition for a remiſſion to Goldſmiths Hall to make his Compoſition, and receive the benefit of <hi>Exon</hi> Articles, He anſwered, That Mr. <hi>Aſh</hi> knew his reſolution as to compound; and that if he had a mind to compound, that he had no money to pay his Compoſition. Which is not only atteſted by Mr. <hi>John Aſh</hi> in his Anſwer annexed to pag. 11. but by the Ladies affirmation to a Juſtice of Peace in the County of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> whoſe Certificate followeth, <hi>viZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="deposition">
               <body>
                  <p>I have ſeveral times (being in diſcourſe with the Lady <hi>Stawell</hi>) heard her to ſay that Mr. <hi>Aſh</hi> hath been a very good friend to her husband, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all thoſe calumnies he hath caſt on the ſaid Mr. <hi>Aſh,</hi> for his endeavouring to ſave the ſaid ſir <hi>Iohns</hi> Eſtate. And about a quarter of a year ſince, being in the company of the ſaid Lady at <hi>Ham,</hi> I acquainted her that Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſh</hi> had not long before that, acquainted me with the paſſage of his viſiting the ſaid ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> at Newgate late at night upon the earneſt importunity of the ſaid Lady, and on aſſurance from her that her husband had then a real mind and will to ſubmit to a compoſition: But when he came there, he found the ſaid ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> to take him up with need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs and impertinent diſcourſes, wholly waving his buſineſs of compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; ſo that the ſaid Lady was enforced to ſay, Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> is it not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for you to abuſe me, but muſt you alſo abuſe your good friend Mr. <hi>Aſh,</hi> who hath at ſuch an unſeaſonable time, and at ſuch a place, come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and by your direction, for the good of you and yours, or words to that effect. All which the ſaid Lady at the time aforeſaid conſented unto, alleadging that it was the truth which I had made relation of. In witneſs whereof I have ſet my hand this 14 day of <hi>December</hi> 1654,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>John Barker.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:119492:22"/>In which ſtubborneſs he continued for the ſpace of four years, and could not be perſwaded to a compoſition, notwithſtanding the many indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of his friends, as Mr. <hi>James Aſhe</hi> hath atteſted upon his knowledg. Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſhe</hi> doth (Anſwer page the 2) affirm that when the Lady <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> (his wife) and Sir <hi>Edward Stawell</hi> his ſon (then in <hi>France</hi>) did ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly ſolicite him, that they might Petition the Parliament to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to compound for the Eſtate, ſince he refuſed it, Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> denied to give his conſent thereunto, threatning his Son to diſherit him if he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted any ſuch thing, and was much incenſed againſt his ſon <hi>Edward</hi> for writing Letters to Mr. <hi>Aſhe</hi> for his admiſſion, ſince his Father re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed it. Mr. <hi>George Longe</hi> was deeply engaged for him (as ſurety) whoſe enſuing Certificate will acquaint you how he ſtood affected unto a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, during his impriſonment in Newgate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>George Longe</hi> Gent. doth certifie that he being engaged, for Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> for ſeveral great ſums of moneys (as by the Counterbonds and other obligations will appear) borrowed by Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> in 1637. and 1638. to purchaſe lands in <hi>Aubury,</hi> in the County of <hi>Wilts,</hi> before the beginning of the late Wars; which being not paid, cauſed the ſaid <hi>George Longe</hi> to go at ſeveral times to the Gaol at Newgate, to intreat him to Petition the Parliament, that he might be admitted to a Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; but the ſaid Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> was much diſcontended with him for his endeavour therein.</p>
            <p>Alſo the ſaid <hi>George Longe</hi> being proſecuted on his ſaid engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> made again his requeſt unto the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> that he would think upon ſome way to make his Compoſition and peace with the Parliament; telling him that the Parliament (as it ſhould ſeem) had taken ſuch notice of his not proſecuting his Articles, or forfeiting them, that an Act was drawing up for the ſale of his and other Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents lands (a Copy or draught whereof the ſaid <hi>George Longe,</hi> at his own coſt procured, and delivered to him, and he read the ſame, being left with him to conſider:) and did further acquaint him, that until the Act was perfected there was hope yet left, ſo as he would betake him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the work, but if he neglected it, that he would not onely undoe his own family, but alſo this Certificant and his. Which courteſie of the ſaid <hi>George Longe,</hi> the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> repaid with diſdainful ſcorn and pride; telling him that he had better Councellors then the ſaid <hi>George Longe:</hi> Which Act paſſed not until about an year after, during which time many of the perſons which were firſt mentioned, got them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſtruck out of the ſaid Act (their cauſes being referred to a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee) and as it is thought ſo might Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> have been, if he had but laid hold of the advice of his meaneſt friends.</p>
            <p>Afterwards his Highneſs the Lord Protector was to make his voyage into <hi>Ireland,</hi> to reduce it: before whoſe going, the ſaid <hi>George Longe</hi> went again to Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> in regard of his the ſaid <hi>Georges</hi> ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, to intreat and perſwade him; and having made ſome relation of his thoughts, did acquaint Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> that he was come the third time to draw a Petition unto his Highneſs (then Lord General) that he would intercede to the Houſe in his behalf, that he might be admitted to a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; wherein the ſaid <hi>George Long</hi> (being ſo nearly concerned) did promiſe unto him, if he would cauſe his Petition to be drawn, and therein
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119492:22"/>
humbly ſtate his caſe, he the ſaid <hi>George</hi> would find ſome means of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing his Petition to be anſwered: In which the ſaid <hi>George Long</hi> could not prevail with the ſaid Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell;</hi> at which this Certificant ſtood amazed to ſee Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> and himſelf ſo near undone; and the ſaid <hi>George Longe</hi> ſo ſenſible, and Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> no way regardful of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and ſo took a ſorrowful farewell. <hi>George Longe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Was not this an apparent wilfulnes in Sr. <hi>Iohn,</hi> that rather then he would Petition the Parliament for his admittance to Compoſition, he would ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard the ruine not of himſelf and Family alone, but of this Gentleman and his houſe, who had ſo friendly and deeply engaged for him? and is not Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> juſtly declared by the Parliament to be not admitted to Compound, when he had for four years ſpace (for the Articles were granted the ninth of April 1646, and the Act that declared his non admiſſion was paſſed the ninth of July 1650) againſt the advice and notwithſtanding the importunities of his friends and ſureties, diſdainfully neglected to Petition to that purpoſe; which by his Articles he ought to have done; for it was not enough for Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> (paſſively) to ſubmit to a Compoſition, but by all means to compaſs it (actively) and to that end the word (ſubmit) in the twelfth Article is explained, by the word (make) in the 22 of the ſame Articles. Sir <hi>John</hi> is pleaſed in his Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance to produce a Petition, which (he ſaith) he delivered to Mr. <hi>John Aſhe;</hi> but indeed hath been lately drawn by Sir <hi>John</hi> of purpoſe to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete his reſolution not to compound; for Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſhe</hi> (Anſ. page 13.) ſaith, that the Petition which (after many amendments and obliterations of the high language therein) Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſhe</hi> was to deliver (as then it was) Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſhe</hi> upon his going into the Country, did by Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment deliver to Mr. <hi>DenZil Hollis,</hi> who refuſed to deliver it, becauſe it deſired his removall to a Priſon more commodious, but not his admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Compoſition; neither doth that Petition in his Remonſtrance mention any ſuch deſire, nor indeed his removal; therefore could not be the Petition delivered to Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſhe,</hi> but one of a later birth. Thus his reſolution not to compound continueth ſtill upon him, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding his now endeavours to perſwade a continual readineſs in him thereunto, if ſuffered.</p>
            <p>In the interim he is (by Order from the Houſe of Commons of the 18. of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> 1646.) at the next Aſſizes held for the County of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſet,</hi> at <hi>Taunton,</hi> found by the then Grand-Iury guilty of High-Treaſon. But that Indictment being (in a legal formality only) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient to bring him to his Trial, was laid aſide; and afterwards (by another Order of the ſame Houſe of the 18 of <hi>February</hi> 1647.) there were three Indictments found againſt him, one for High-treaſon, and two for Murder; one for killing of <hi>Robert Osborn,</hi> at <hi>Marſhals-Elm</hi> (being the firſt blood ſhed in the Weſt of <hi>England</hi> in that quarrel) and the other for the murder (not execution) of <hi>Chriſtopher Viccary.</hi> Which Indictments were found by a Grand Iury conſiſting of nineteen Eſquires and Gentlemen (ſome whereof have been ſince, and now are in the Commiſſion of the Peace) four whereof only were of <hi>Taunton, (viZ.</hi> Mr. <hi>Richard Bovet,</hi> Mr. <hi>Samuel Whetcomb,</hi> Mr. <hi>Philip Lyſſant,</hi> and Mr. <hi>George Powel</hi>) the reſt living in ſeveral places in that County;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119492:23"/>
and but two of theſe four (<hi>viZ.</hi> Mr. <hi>Richard Bovet</hi> and Mr. <hi>Powel</hi>) had then obtained Iudgments againſt Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> and yet thoſe legally and upon evidence, and defence made: The one for Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> taking away unjuſtly 1200<hi>l.</hi> worth of Mr. <hi>Bovets</hi> eſtate; the other for his cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty towards Mr. <hi>Powel</hi> as aforeſaid; and Mr. <hi>Bovet</hi> (only) hath ſince chaſed a parcel of Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> Eſtate.</p>
            <p>But doe all or any of theſe allegations invalid thoſe Verdicts found by fifteen more, beſides thoſe four of <hi>Taunton?</hi> Becauſe Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> moſt frequent and greateſt acts of Treaſon, and the Murder of <hi>Viccary</hi> were committed in <hi>Taunton,</hi> was it not fit that ſome of the Jury ſhould be of <hi>Taunton,</hi> that could beſt judge of theſe his acts? And becauſe ſome of them had obtained Verdicts againſt him upon ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent proofs, for injuries done unto them, can it be any exception againſt their Verdict; eſpecially ſince they had long before the time of the Verdict recovered the ſame?</p>
            <p>And as weak is the laſt allegation: Becauſe one of them hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed ſome Eſtate expoſed to ſale in 1651. Therefore he was no competent Iuror 1647. (four years before) when ſuch expoſal to ſale could not without a ſpirit of divination be before ſeen, and might have been prevented if he had pleaſed; but being now ſold, he catcheth at every twig to recover it.</p>
            <p>However the truth of thoſe Verdicts and Indictments is ſince con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Iudgment of the High Court of Iuſtice, upon Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> Plea of <hi>Not guilty,</hi> and the Depoſitions of ſeveral Witneſſes to that purpoſe; as is certified under the ſubſcriptions of three and twenty of that Court, and manifeſted by the recital of the proceedings of that Court in the Remonſtrance.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> being thus found guilty by three ſeveral Indictments of Treaſon and two Murders, and ſtill refuſing the mercy of his Articles, the Parliament in honour of Iuſtice, and upon conſideration of his forfeiture of Articles, did on the 14 of <hi>March</hi> 1648. and two years and a half and more after his firſt Commitment, Order his Trial upon theſe Indictments at the Upper-Bench bar, where his Expreſſions were more inſolent, and his diſownings of the preſent Authority greater then at any time before: And ſo far was Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> (after ſo long impriſonment) from accepting the benefit of his Articles, that he did not then mention them in order to his exemption from that Trial; but on the contrary, diſtinguiſhing Mr. Iuſtice <hi>Bacon</hi> from Mr. Iuſtice <hi>Roll,</hi> owned the firſt, as one ſitting by the Kings Commiſſion; but diſowned the latter, being appointed by the Parliament under the Great Seal by them approved; which Seal he termed a Counterfeit, and accuſed the then Sollicitor-Generall of high treaſon for proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting againſt him in the name of the Parliament, as was by ſeveral Witneſſes proved before the High Court of Iuſtice.</p>
            <p>And as Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſh</hi> affirmeth, uttered words to this effect, <hi>viZ. My offence is not Treaſon for which I am here arraigned, but becauſe I would not permit the Committee of Goldſmiths Hall to pick my purſe, and give my conſent to pay a ſum of mony for the redemption of my Eſtate which is unjustly taken from me.</hi> Which ſpeeches, if they had fallen from one formerly innocent, had been an offence of an high nature; but being
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119492:23"/>
ſpoken by ſir <hi>Iohn,</hi> a perſon guilty (and ſo found by ſeveral Grand Iuries, and at ſeveral times) of Treaſon, Murder, and other high offences; And by one that came into the Parliament-Quarters under the pretence of a Compoſition; and in that conjuncture of time, when divers Garriſons held yet out for the late King, and ſome Ships had renegaded the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-ſervice: and in one of the higheſt Iudicatures whither multitudes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorted to obſerve his deportment, became not a Compounder, much ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravated his former offences, muſt prove prejudicial to the Parliaments affairs, and contrary to the 21 of <hi>Exceter</hi> Articles, and to ſir <hi>Iohns</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement and ſubſcription at the <hi>Guild</hi> Hall, and was doubtleſs a breach of his Articles.</p>
            <p>And although perhaps theſe inſolencies were not Treaſon within the Cognizance of an inferior or ordinary Judicature, yet might the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment adjudge them ſo, which they have done: For in their Act of ſale, they have mentioned Treaſon committed by him; which muſt be his miſcarriages ſince his Articles, for his former were pardoned: And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be granted they do not amount unto Treaſon, yet they may be a breach of Articles; for it is not Treaſon only that doth break them, inferior offences may prove a breach, the breach of good behaviour (and certainly his miſcarriages are of no leſs nature) is a forfeiture of a pardon; and why not of Articles? Truely much more: for pardon (though of grace) is grounded upon the compact and agreement of the whole Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but theſe Articles are but the agreement of certain perſons thereof; of the Army with Traitors. And although by the third Article of <hi>Exon,</hi> certain enumerated Acts are made a breach of thoſe Articles; yet que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionleſs other matters not enumerated, may be a breach; whereof theſe of ſir <hi>John</hi> are ſome: and (it ſeems) have been ſo adjudged by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: For in the Debate of all Acts and Reſolutions of theirs againſt ſir <hi>John,</hi> they ſtill had a conſideration of his Articles, and adjudged theſe his miſcarriages a breach of them; and therefore declared him not to be admitted to Compoſition, having forfeited the benefit thereof. And although the Articles bind not ſir <hi>John</hi> in point of his judgement, yet they reſtrain him from all open and overt expreſſions thereof, to the prejudice of the Commonwealth. A man in private thoughts, deemeth another man to be a thief (perhaps knoweth him to be one:) This judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, this knowledg, the Law taketh no notice of:</p>
            <p>But let him declare ſuch his thoughts, judgement, or knowledge, by ſaying he is a Thief; theſe open words being prejudicial to the party whereof the words were ſpoken, make him liable to an Action; and if he proves it not, to repair him in damage: Sir <hi>John</hi> might without da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage have kept his judgement to himſelf; but expreſſing it in ſuch inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and prejudicial language to the affairs of Parliament, he forfeited his Articles.</p>
            <p>Which his deportment being reported to the Houſe of Commons, they proceeded at that time no further againſt him in that Court; but having then conſideration of the Articles of <hi>Exon,</hi> and to preſerve the faith of their Armies from all colour of violation; they ſtill reſerved their mercy for him, if he had but then implored it.</p>
            <p>But ſir <hi>John</hi> continued in his averſe reſolution, out of a confidence of the late Kings reſtitution to his Power and Authority; and a deſigne
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119492:24"/>
thereby to receive his whole Eſtate gratis, with a great reward for his many ſufferings in owning and juſtifying the late Kings Cauſe beyond a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his party, being the only Subject of his, that refuſed to comply with the Parliament, when he might, and was earneſtly invited thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; which aim of his is apparent: For Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſh</hi> doth tell us that he ſent unto the late King at <hi>Hampton</hi>-Court, deſiring him to take notice of the great ſufferings he had undergone for his Majeſties Cauſe, and did let him know the hopes he had of his Majeſties great favour and reward for him, when he ſhould be reſtored. And Mr. <hi>Iames Aſh</hi> teſtifieth, that the Lady <hi>Stawell</hi> told him that ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> did ſtill flatter his hopes to have the King reſtored; and although there were daily leſs hopes, yet his faith continued ſtrong; nay beſides the teſtimony of theſe two per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of honour (and by the teſtimony of two witneſſes, each truth ought to be tryed) if half an eye did but look into his carriage from his firſt coming before the Committee at Goldſmiths Hall, untill his tryal by the High-Court of Juſtice, it could be nothing but diſownings, contempts, and opprobrious language of the preſent Government and Authority, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riding of Compounders, and not the leaſt claim of the benefit of his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, as long as his hopes of favour and ſingularity remained: For ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> never pleaded, nor ſo much as ever pretended to thoſe Articles, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till ſome time after the late Kings death, although in the mean time there were brought and obtained againſt him divers Actions and Iudgements for acts by him done before thoſe Articles, and relating to the wars; which actions amounted to the total of 7000 <hi>l.</hi> (as himſelf affirmeth) and to which actions he never pleaded thoſe Articles (although he might) but ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the general iſſue of not guilty, or ſuffered Iudgement to paſs againſt him by confeſſion or default. When he was arraigned at the Upper-Bench-Bar for his life, he did not ſo much as mention thoſe Articles: He now ſaith in his Remonſtrance pag. 30. that upon his moving to plead ſpecially, the Court did order that he ſhould bring in his ſpecial Plea the firſt day of the next Term, and did aſſigne him Councel for that purpoſe; but what that ſpecial Plea was, or intended to be, whether touching his Articles, or any other matter, ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> is not pleaſed to acquaint us; hower, during this time ſir <hi>Iohns</hi> deportment was full of diſdain towards the Authority of Parliament: High it was at his firſt coming to Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths Hall, higher at the ſecond being there; and higheſt at his arraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the Upper-Bench-Bar: all which do manifeſt his intention not to compound, through his ambitious hopes aforeſaid. But when by the Kings death his hopes began to ſink, and were abſolutely loſt by the King of <hi>Scots</hi> (the late Kings pretended ſucceſſor) his taking the Covenant, and thereby engaging againſt ſir <hi>Iohn,</hi> his Cauſe and Intereſt; then, and not before, he abated the height of his inſolencies; how milde then he grew! witneſs his carriage (ſunk even to a dejection) before the High-Court of Iuſtice; and how fearfull! his endeavour to eſcape out of New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate (being thither committed for High-Treaſon) doth teſtifie. And then, and not before, he took up his pretences and flew back to the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of thoſe Articles, which he formerly ſlighted; and to regain the loſt benefit of them, he inſinuates with the Army, ſuggeſteth unto them, the great diſhonour if their faith ſhould be queſtioned; and that the higheſt ſecurity that the world affords, is engaged for his Indempnity;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119492:24"/>
and his confidence of reſtitution is ſuch, that his Agents give out, that Commiſſary General <hi>Whaley</hi> will leave no ſtone unturned to preſerve it; to the great ſcandal and abuſe of that perſon of valour and integrity.</p>
            <p>Whereas it is true, that the Faith of an Army is a high ſecurity, and the honour of it ought to be as pretious as the apple of the eye; which Faith, which Honour, ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> had once engaged for his Indempnity; but ſuch an Indempnity only, that he might the freelier make his Compoſition with the Parliament. But when Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> did not endeavour, but ſlight, nay contemn his Compoſition; and during his ſtay in the Parliament-Quarters, did (by colour of that faith) in a preſumptuous manner diſown their Authority, in their Committees, in their Courts of Iuſtice, and in their very Houſe, he hath abuſed the end for which this faith was given, the Armies faith is diſingaged, and it will be a diſhonour unto them now to ſupport him, whoſe offences cry aloud for puniſhment, and who hath in ſo high a nature, abuſed the end and truſt of their engagement, and ſcorned their mercy, otherwiſe then to make uſe of it, to advance his own ambition, and that very deſigne againſt which the Army did fight: when a mutual faith is paſſed between man and wife, the ſecurity is greater, and as great as the faith of Articles; and the wife may with greater reaſon, challenge performance from her husband, then a Traitor can upon his Articles; yet if the woman ſhall become an Adultereſs, ſhe hath abuſed that faith, and the end for which it was given, and the husband is diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged without the leaſt breach of his honour, or faith unviolated: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doth the faith of the Army remain, notwithſtanding ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, Trials, and ſale of his Eſtate, and the rather for that he that now layeth ſuch hold on the Articles of <hi>Exon,</hi> brake his own with the Town of <hi>Taunton,</hi> and committed <hi>Dunſcomb</hi> to rot in the Gaol, although his perſon was indemnified by the Articles of <hi>Briſtoll.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> after a recital in his Remonſtrance of theſe tranſactions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, mentioneth the erection of the Court of Articles (in time, 18 <hi>Iune</hi> 1649.) and his Petition thereunto, to be relieved upon theſe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; upon which Petition (he ſaith, Remonſt. pag. 35.) no proceedings were made by that Court; but tels you not the reaſon; which in truth was for that (as they anſwered his Petition) that they could not relieve him, ſtanding committed by the Parliament for High-Treaſon; well knowing that by Law, that Court could not by general words of their Act of Erection, intermeddle with ſir <hi>Iohns</hi> relief, ſeeing he was particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly committed by the Houſe of Commons for High-Treaſon, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by implicitely adjudged to have either broken, or neglected the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of his Articles.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="response_to_petition">
               <body>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:119492:25"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>Painted Chamber, <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 
                        <date>Die Veneris, 13 July 1644.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>By the Committee appointed for Relief upon ARTICLES of WAR.</signed>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THe Petition of Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> Knight, was this day read, and the Councel on the Petitioners behalf heard: And it was moved that Bail might be taken for the ſaid Sir <hi>John,</hi> or that a Keeper might attend him to his Councel, for the clearing and diſpatch of his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs. Hereupon it was urged by the Councel for the Commonwealth, That the Parliament, who were the Supream Authority, and from whom all other Courts were derivative, had (as was confeſſed in ſir <hi>Johns</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition) committed him for High-Treaſon, and levying War againſt the Parliament, and commanded that he ſhould be detained Priſoner untill they gave further Order: So that no conſideration was to be had by any other Power under them, as to his Bail, or enlargement without their leave: But his Councel was informed, that if they had any thing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to move on the Petitioners behalf, they ſhould be heard; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they deſired time to adviſe: Which was accordingly granted untill Wedneſday.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>A true Copy.</hi> JOHN WILSON, <hi>Dep. Regiſt.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Now from the time that ſir <hi>John</hi> was arraigned at the Upper-Bench-Bar (which) as himſelf ſaith, was in <hi>May</hi> 1649. there did efflux 13 months, untill the time that the Parliament paſſed their Act for ſir <hi>Iohns</hi> Tryal by the High-Court of Iuſtice, which paſſed 9 <hi>Iuly</hi> 1650. during which time they patiently expected his reformation; but finding him of the ſame thoughts, did by that Act order his Trial by that Court and did in two places thereof, mention that ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> was not admitted to compound.</p>
            <p>And therefore, when in the tryal of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> for Treaſon and other offences (amongſt which the killing of <hi>Robert Oſborne</hi> at <hi>Marſhals Elme,</hi> and the hanging of <hi>Chriſtopher Viccary</hi> in <hi>Taunton,</hi> were two) upon hearing all the Evidences and Witneſſes produced on the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, and of the Priſoner, it was agreed by that whole Court, (for ſo they certified to the Parliament) as by the ſame tranſcribed in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance, page 37. 38. appeareth) that he was guilty of the Treaſon, and other high offences charged on him; that Court ought to have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to ſentence, his ſpecial plea of Articles notwithſtanding; neither indeed ſhould that plea have been admitted, after that the Parliament
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119492:25"/>
had by their Act declared, that he was not admitted to compound; and that, that Court ſhould try him, as one not admitted thereunto; which Declaration no inferior or ſubordinate Court or authority whatſoever hath power to examine or queſtion.</p>
            <p>And all Examinations, Reſolutions, and other proceedings of that Court, touching thoſe Articles and Plea thereof, are void and extrajudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial; and Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> ſtands guilty by the Judgement of that Court of high Treaſon, and other the offences aboveſaid: and by Act of Parliament declared not admitted to compound.</p>
            <p>This his Guilt being certified to the Parliament, by the high Court of Juſtice, with a ceſſer of ſentence; in reſpect of his Articles the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament upon reading of that Certificate (10 <hi>Iune</hi> 1651.) reſented the ſame, yet by reaſon thereof ſpared his life, but paſſed an Act of the 16 of <hi>Iune</hi> 1651. (a month thereafter) whereby they adjudge ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> to have forfeited his Eſtate for Treaſon, and thereupon veſted the actual poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of that Eſtate in certain Truſtees and their heirs, in order to the ſale thereof; which Lands are ſince ſold accordingly, and the moneys diſpoſed of for the uſe of the Commonwealth; ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> being in that Act firſt named, and before others of higher degree: Which Act and Iudgement, being the Act and Iudgement of all the People of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> incluſively; and the ſame judgement being ſince fully executed, and the Eſtate of ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> in fact ſold and diſpoſed of by and according to that Act; and the Purchaſers thereof by force of their reſpective bargains in the actual and peaceable poſſeſſion thereof, theſe conſequences will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and be neceſſarily deduced.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Reaſons and cauſes of that Iudgement cannot be examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or queſtioned out of the Houſe it ſelf: Whether they paſſed that their Iudgement for Treaſonable acts by him done before his Articles, in regard they adjudge his Articles to be either neglected in perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, or broken by all or any his refuſals or miſdemeanors aboveſaid? or whether they adjudged thoſe miſdemeanors either joyntly or ſeveral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to be a new Treaſon, and by conſequence a forfeiture of his Eſtate ſince his Articles? Or whether for any, and for any other act of his, or cauſe, they paſſed their Iudgement againſt him? It will therefore ſeem very unreaſonable, and be of dangerous conſequence, if the Purchaſers (me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat or immediat) ſhould be now enforced (for defence of ſuch their Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions) to ſearch into, and produce the reaſons and cauſes thereof, eſpecially ſince the Purchaſers are meer ſtrangers thereunto. 2. That all the Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations and other proceedings, and very Iudgement of the Court of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles (on the ſaid Iudgement of Parliament) (although an Act of Parliament erected it after that Iudgement given) were extrajudicial, againſt the fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Laws of this Commonwealth, and of bad example.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Coram non Iudice;</hi> When that Court (under pretence of a general Act of Relief upon Articles) did intermeddle with the Caſe of ſir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> touching his perſon and Eſtate, his Eſtate being already adjudged by Act of Parliament to be forfeited; and the impriſonment of his perſon remaining indiſcuſſed in that very Houſe, eſpecially after the Parliament had</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="resolution">
               <body>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:119492:26"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Thurſday, <hi>Febr.</hi> 24. 1652.</date>
                     </dateline>
Reſolved,</opener>
                  <p>THat the Cauſe of Sir <hi>John Stawel</hi> upon his pretence of Title to Articles, be reſumed to the conſideration and determination of the Parliament; and that the Commiſsioners for giving relief to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons upon Articles, do forbear to proceed any further therein, untill the Parliament take further order.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Hen. Scobell,</hi> Cler. Parl.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Which Reſolves (amounting unto an explanation of that Act of Reviver) determined not with the diſſolution of the Parliament, but doth remain annexed to it (as a Codicil) taking away the Iuriſdiction of that Court in the Caſe of Sir <hi>Iohn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Theſe proceedings were <hi>coram non Iudice,</hi> in regard of a Proviſo in that Act of Reviver, in theſe words, <hi>viZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Provided, That ſuch perſon or perſons claiming benefit of Articles as aforeſaid, have not forfeited the ſame by breach or non-performance of what is or was on their part to be performed, ſince their Articles were granted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the Parliament having declared, if not adjudged Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> not to be admitted to Compound, have adjudged or declared that Sir <hi>John</hi> hath forfeited his Articles either by breach or non-performance; either of which Judgment or Declaration the Court of Articles could not draw into queſtion. And therefore is Sir <hi>John</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in that <hi>Proviſo,</hi> and without the juriſdiction of that Court.</p>
            <p>It is a fundamental, That a Judgment of Parliament ſhould not be reverſed or annulled by any ſubordinate or delegated Court, Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cature or Authority whatſoever, or otherwiſe then by the immediate power of Parliament, which power cannot be tranſmitted to any other Judicature.</p>
            <p>The Court of Articles have adjudged, That Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> (from and after Compoſition made as aforeſaid) ſhall have the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of his Eſtate freed and diſcharged from all ſequeſtrations and ſeiſures whatſoever, and ſhall enjoy the ſame without any claim, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, impediment or moleſtation of the ſaid Truſtees, or of the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vivors or Survivor of them, they or any of their heirs.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the words of that Judgment, as it is recited in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance, <hi>pag.</hi> 71. Which Judgment in reſpect of this Eſtate, is no otherwiſe then an annihilation of that Act of Parliament by this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Court, under pretence of a power tranſmitted unto them by the general words of the Act of Reviver, when as a ſpecial Act could not give any ſuch power of annihilation.</p>
            <p>The Legiſlative power by the fundamental laws remaineth ſolely and undoubtedly in the Parliament, and cannot be transferred to any inferior Judicature whatſoever. Of which power, the Abrogation or Repeal of former Laws, is a branch or part.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:119492:26"/>But this Judgment of the Court of <hi>Articles</hi> (in reſpect of the Eſtate of Sir <hi>Iohn</hi>) doth amount unto a Repeal of that Act of diſpoſing this Eſtate, by a power pretended to be delegated to that Court by the general words of that Act of Reviver.</p>
            <p>It is of bad example for that Court of Articles to take cogniſance of the Cauſe of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> the ſame being depending before the Supreme Authority of the Nation: when as their Predeceſſors (who had the ſame, if not greater power) for that very reaſon forbare to give Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> any relief in that behalf; And when the High Court of Juſtice for the ſame cauſe forbore their ſentence, and did ſubmit it to the judgment of the Houſe, although their Act was particular, and the Act of Reviving the Court of Articles in generall words. And the example is heighthened, after that the Parliament-Votes had prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them any further intermedling, to reſume the cogniſance of the Cauſe, and to proceed to judgment, and by that judgment (in reſpect of the Eſtate) to intrench upon the priviledge of Parliament, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſing the Judgments of Parliament, and repealing the Acts thereof; and when the Judges, Members of that Committee, and the beſt and fundamental Expoſitors of Acts of Parliament, (the Parliament that made them being diſſolved) did deliver their opinions againſt ſuch juriſdiction.</p>
            <p>The Examinations, Judgment, and Proceedings of that Court being <hi>coram non Judice,</hi> and againſt Fundamentals, are meerly void in Law, eſpecially when that Judgment is grounded upon no proofs, the proofs taken by the High Court of Juſtice being taken extrajudicially as aboveſaid, and are therefore (in a Legal conſtruction) Nullities. Which gives a full and ſhort Anſwer to that large recital thereof in the <hi>Remonſtrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And although the Certificates, Orders and Awards of that Court of Articles are binding and concluſive to all Courts of Juſtice, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees, &amp;c. any Law, Order or Ordinance to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; yet hath not that Court ſuch ſole and ſupreme power or ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, as to controll the Acts or Reſolutions of the Parliament (the ſource of their power) and eſpecially when their Act beginneth with <hi>Courts of Juſtice,</hi> which are of an inferior juriſdiction. Nor can it now, neither ought it to be ſuppoſed that the aforeſaid Acts, Orders, Reſolutions, Iudgments and Proceedings of that Parliament, were, or were given in breach or violation of any of the Articles of <hi>Exon,</hi> eſpecially they ſtill having a conſideration thereof; in the violation of which Articles, the faith of the Army and honour and juſtice of the Nation is ſo highly concerned. But it ſhall and ought to be preſumed, that Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> by ſome or all of the miſdemeanors and neglects afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or by other acts of his beſt known to that Parliament, had in the judgment thereof forfeited and loſt the benefit of his Articles.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John,</hi> by way of objection, (<hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> p. 74.) reciteth a Clauſe in that Act of Sale, in theſe words, <hi>viZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Nevertheleſs upon truſt and confidence that the ſaid</hi> William Skinner <hi>and others the perſons abovenamed, or any five or more of them, ſhall
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119492:27"/>
have, hold and enjoy all and every the premiſes, and every of them ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto ſuch truſts and uſes, as by this Act, or in and by authority of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſhall be hereafter further directed and appointed, and ſhall diſpoſe of the ſame accordingly.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>And from thence would infer,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That this power of limiting the truſts of thoſe Lands, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the Parliament in relation to the Articles of War, by them confirmed; that in regard they had ratified divers of them, and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently bound themſelves in Faith, Honour, and Juſtice to make good, and could not take notice of ſuch as had right or claim to the ſame; they thereof provided, according to this reſerved power, that the Truſtees ſhould diſpoſe of Lands accordingly.</p>
            <p>In anſwer whereof it muſt be premiſed,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Articles of Exon were confirmed by both Houſes the fourth of <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1647. And this Act paſſed the ſixth of July 1651. almoſt four years after.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the words of that clauſe refer to truſts and uſes onely, which ſhould for the future be directed and appointed by that Act, or authority of Parliament.</p>
            <p>It will then follow, that the truſts if any of the Articles of Exon can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the truſts, mentioned in that Act being precedent to it, not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent.</p>
            <p>That the Act for ſale paſſed for no cauſes mentioned in thoſe Articles, but for others, and for ought appeaes, for offences of a later perpetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>That it was well known to that Parliament, that Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> did claim the benefit of thoſe Article; for the Parliament had at ſeveral times before, and at the time of the paſſing of this Act, his very Articles in conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and deemed them forfeited by him.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing that Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> doth infer is, that the reviving after that of the Court of Articles, was a Declaration of the uſes and truſts of that Act of Sale; ſeeing to that perſons grieved contrary to thoſe Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, this Court was conſtituted to do them right, any Law, Order or Ordinance to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>But Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> hath miſtaken the Act; the words are not, that the Court of Articles ſhould releive the party within Articles, any Law to the contrary; but that the Certificate of that Court ſhould be binding to all inferiour Courts of Juſtice, any Law to the contrary notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>Again, by the Act of Sale, the truſts of that Act are declared, &amp; the land ſold, and ſetled according to that Declaration; and therefore the Patlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot by vertue of that reſervation, declare any contrary or other truſts, nor did by their Act of reviver make uſe of their former power; (having already executed the ſame) in overthrow of thoſe ſales executed by vertue of that Act of ſale; eſpecially when, as hath been ſhewn, Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> is a party — excepted out of that Act.</p>
            <p>After which Act of Sale, and not before, Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> doth pretend to Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition the Parliament, for admiſſion to compoſition; which Petition (as he alledgeth by his Remonſtrance page 39) he delivered unto Mr. <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:119492:27"/>
but whether Mr. <hi>Garland</hi> did, or thought fit to preſent it to the Parliament, in regard of Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> former actions is not declared, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the Parliament refuſed it and juſtly: for Gods vice-gerents do often Act like God himſelf; who when after a long forbearance on his part, and an obſtinate continuance in evil on mans part, he reſolveth to puniſh; he doth execute the ſame accordingly, notwithſtanding the Prayers and ſupplications of the ſinner, to whom he then turneth a deaf year.</p>
            <p>This might the Parliament do, Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> ſlightning of their mercy, and the neceſſity of their Juſtice urging them to it. Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith (Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance pag. 40.) that at the time of the paſſing of the Act of the 29. of <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1652. for reviveing the Court of Articles, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors were tendered (he conceiveth by the Purchaſers) the one of the 28 of <hi>Septemb.</hi> 1652. in theſe words, <hi>viZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Provided that this Act, or any thing therein contained, ſhall not extend, nor cinſtrained to ixtend to prejudice, alter, or make void any Reſolutions, Votes or Judgments given in the Parliament, touching any of the Articles aforeſaid (or any perſons) claiming thereby.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other of the day following in theſe words, <hi>viZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Provided alwayes, and be it further enacted and declared, That no real or perſonal Eſtate, which hath been ſetled, conveyed, or aſſured to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons, by vertue of any Act, Ordinance, or Order of this preſent Parliament, ſhall be made null, vacated, or otherwiſe determined, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of by the Commiſsioners, named in this Act or by their Authority; but if they ſhall ſee cauſe of reſtitution, by vertue of Articles ſubject un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their CogniZance, they make a word not in ſpecie againſt the particular perſon or perſons, upon whom ſuch Eſtate or Eſtates ſhall be ſetled, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed, or aſſured, but invalue to be ſatisfied by ſuch other Lands or Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new, as the Parliament ſhall direct any thing in this Act, or the former; which is hereby revived to the contrary notwithſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe he ſaith (after the ſecond reading, the laſt after the firſt reading) did paſs in the Negative, which proviſo tending to the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation of that benefit; which the Houſe was moſt honourably pleaſed to grant, and allow to ſuch perſons as ſhould claim releife by Articles were both received; and it was reſolved upon the queſtion in the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative, which he prayeth may be ſpecially obſerved.</p>
            <p>It may be thought preſumption in Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> to intimate any reaſon or grounds of the refuſal of thoſe Proviſoes, and it would be modeſty in us not to imitate him; yet in anſwer to that his intimation, we ſay that the Parliament (as appeareth by their proceedings intended ſo much in the caſe of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell;</hi> though perhaps they would not have ſuch a general proviſo incerted, either becauſe their was no Judgement, Vote, or Reſolution of that Parliament touching Articles; but in the Caſe of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> or becauſe they preſumed, as well they might; that their inferior (deivrative) Court of Articles would not call inqueſtion any of their proceedings; but as ſoon as they did find that, that Court had proceeded in the Caſe of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> they forthwith by their
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119492:28"/>
Reſolution of the 24 of <hi>Febr.</hi> aboveſaid, prohibited them any further proceedings, eſpecially when that Court began to proceed to ſentence contrary to their judgement, untill that time wiſely forbearing their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition, in expectation of that ſubordinate Courts ſubmiſſion to their Declaration of Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> not admittance to compound, and their diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of his Eſtate.</p>
            <p>There is likewiſe a Proviſo in that Act of reviver, which in effect is the ſame with the recited Proviſo, and is in theſe words, <hi>viZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Provided, That ſuch perſon or perſons, claiming benefit of Articles as aforeſaid, have not forfeited the ſame by breach or nonperformance of what is, or was on their part, to be performed ſince thoſe Articles were ſo granted.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>And there cannot be a more ſupream Declaration or Judgement, then that of the Parliament it ſelf; that Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> had forfeited the benefit of his Artitles: and therefore the Caſe of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> the onely Caſe depending in Parliament, touching Articles was already provided for, and by conſequence that Proviſo needleſs.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Proviſo ſeemeth as needleſs to be inſerted in this Act of Reviver; for ſince it doth revive the former Act, and doth enable that newly erected Court, to put in execution all and every the powers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in that former Act; one of which powers is, to releive and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs the parties complaining, ſo far as in juſtice they ought to have by the ſaid Articles, by reſtitution in ſpecie or in value, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Proviſo ſpeaks no more then what was enacted in the very body of that Act; and for that reaſon, doubtleſs was laid aſide.</p>
            <p>The next material thing for our Anſwer, is the Letter of Sir <hi>Anthony Irbie,</hi> mentioned in the Remonſtrance, page 59. to be directed to Mr. <hi>Tracy Pauncefoot</hi> Reg. of the Court of Articles, and at large inſerted, and becauſe he did Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> ſuch good ſervice, by his ſaid Letter; Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> hath produced him as a Witneſs, before the preſent Committee of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, where his examination was in theſe words, <hi>viZ.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <pb n="53" facs="tcp:119492:28"/>
                        <head>The Examination of <hi>Anthony Irby,</hi> Knight, taken the <hi>16</hi> of <hi>November 1654.</hi> before the Committee of Parliament to whom the Lord <hi>Cravens</hi> Petition is referr'd; being produced as a Witneſs on the behalf of Sir <hi>John Stawel,</hi> whoſe Petition is referred by the Parliament to this Committee.</head>
                        <p>VVHo ſaith, That he was one of the Committee for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding ſitting at <hi>Goldſmiths Hall,</hi> and was preſent there when Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> did prefer his Petition to compound: And ſaith that the ſame was ſo preferred within the time limited by the Articles of <hi>Exeter,</hi> as appeared by the Paſs of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax.</hi> And ſaith that the ſaid Petition was read at the board, but ſomething therein was diſliked; for Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> did not acknowledge his Delinquencie, nor would he take the Covenant and Negative Oath. And further ſaith, that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> did not behave himſelf misbecomingly, as this Deponent conceiveth, only did inſiſt upon the Articles of <hi>Exeter,</hi> and ſaid that by them he was to be admitted to Compoſition; and he this Examinant took no exceptions at his carriage. And ſaith, that in thoſe times there was want of mony, and it was his opinion that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> ought to compound.</p>
                        <p>And further ſaith, That at that time this Examinant did not know of any body that was about to buy any part of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> Eſtate: but ſaith, That about two or three yeares ago (as he remembreth) he was at Sir <hi>Abraham Williams</hi> his houſe, being about the time of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> Trial for his life, or preſently after, as he remembreth; and there he met Sir <hi>Edward Baynton,</hi> and enquired of him the reaſon of the proſecution of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell.</hi> And Sir <hi>Edward Baynton</hi> then told this Examinant, That there was a Gentleman who would have bought a Mannor of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire</hi> or <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> (he cannot tell whether) and that he the ſaid Sir <hi>Edward Baynton</hi> had ſome intereſt in part of it, and had offered, if Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> would ſell his part, he alſo would ſell his other part; but ſaid, that afterwards he was ſorry for that offer, becauſe he conceived that was the original of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> troubles.</p>
                        <p>And this Examinant further ſaith, That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> came pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually within the time limited by his Articles; for that the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee for compounding gave him a time to appear after the date of the time given by the ſaid Articles, on purpoſe that the Committee might ſhew him no favor when the time given by the Articles was out. And ſaith, That Sir <hi>Edward Baynton</hi> told him this Examinant, that the perſon who would buy the ſaid Mannor, was Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſh.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And this Examinant further ſaith, That one of the Members of that Committee, being the Chairman, told the Committee that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> was without with a Petition, but ſaid the ſame was failing in many circumſtances. And ſaith, That after the Caſe then in debate was ended, (which was one <hi>Berkleys,</hi> as this Deponent now remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers)
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119492:29"/>
Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> was called in. And this Examinant being now demanded whether Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> had ſubſcribed not to bear arms a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament, as was required by his Articles: This Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſaith, that there was a Committee who ſate in <hi>Goldſmiths Hall</hi> to take Subſcriptions, without which, as he remembreth, Delinquents were not to ſtay within the Lines of Communication; but ſaith, that he doth not remember that ever he ſaw any Certificate that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> had ſubſcribed not to bear arms, nor did he ever ſee the Certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate of any other perſon to that purpoſe that came to compound. And this Examinant further ſaith, That the Committee had an Order of Parliament not to compound with any that did not take the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant and Negative oath, which latter the Committee had power to adminiſter, and the ſame was tendred to Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> but he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to take it, and ſaid he was excuſed by his Articles. And this Examinant further faith, That it was not then objected againſt Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel,</hi> that he had not ſubſcribed the Engagement not to bear arms againſt the Parliament.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Being Croſs-examined on the behalf of the Commonwealth, He ſaith,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>That he doth not remember that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> ſaid, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee were Traitors or Delinquents. That to his remembrance, they had no Order of Parliament that perſons ſhould acknowledge their Delinquencie before they were admitted to compound; but the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee made ſuch an agreement amongſt themſelves: And ſaith, that ſome of the Committee did ſay, that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> Petition was rather a Remonſtrance then a Petition. And ſaith, that there was no Particular of his Eſtate annexed to his Petition, nor was it ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſo to do, but the Particular was uſually delivered after ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to a Compoſition. And ſaith, that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> did refuſe the Covenant and Negative oath upon account of his Articles; and that the ſubſcription not to bear Arms, was not to be made before them, but in another place before they came to them. And ſaith, That he was neer Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> when he was with the Committee, but did not hear any particular ill language given by him to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, as he remembreth; but ſaith that his carriage was then as it was uſually, not very pleaſant or Courtly.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="deposition">
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:119492:29"/>
                        <head>Sir <hi>David Watkins</hi> examined at the ſame time on Sir <hi>John Stawels</hi> part,</head>
                        <opener>Saith,</opener>
                        <p>THat he was of the Committee for Compounding, and was there when Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> came and preſented his Petition to the Committee, which was within four moneths from the 8. of <hi>April.</hi> And ſaith, that he came in a civil manner, but did not acknowledge his Delinquencie, nor would take the Negative oath, and was refuſed to be admitted upon that account. And ſaith, that he doth not remember any Order of Parliament that did forbid them to Compound with perſons that did not acknowledge themſelves De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents, but ſuch as had not taken the Oath and Covenant. And ſaith that he ſaw the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> his Paſs dated in <hi>April,</hi> and that he doth account four moneths after the rate of 28 dayes to a moneth. And ſaith, that he doth not know that any Certificate was brought to them touching Subſcription not to bear Arms, either in this or any caſe of perſons compounding upon thoſe Articles; and ſaith, that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> not ſubſcribing, was not objected againſt him at that time.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Being Croſs-examined on the behalf of the Commonwealth, He ſaith,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>That ſome did ſay, That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawels</hi> Petition was rather a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance then a Petition; but the title was <hi>A Petition.</hi> But he had not acknowledged his Delinquencie, nor taken the Negative Oath and Covenant; and for that reaſon he conceives it was called a Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance. That the Committee were informed he had ſubſcribed not to bear Arms againſt the Parliament.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Sir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> being called in after the Company were withdrawn, and asked whether there were any private diſcourſe at the Committee to Sir <hi>John Stawels</hi> prejudice,</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>HE ſaith, that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> being without the dore, the Chair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man went out, and on his return told this Examinant, That Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> was a great Enemy, had raiſed Arms againſt the Parliament, drew the firſt blood in the Weſt of <hi>England;</hi> that his Petition was not valid, he acknowledged no Delinquencie, had not taken the Negative Oath; and ſaith that the Committee preſſed him to it, and upon refuſall gave him time till his Articles were out, becauſe then they knew how to deal with him; and ſaith that the Committee did not meddle with ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, for that was to be done by particular Committees ſeparated from them, becauſe that concern'd Delinquents ſtay in Town: but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſee that they did take the Negative Oath and Covenant. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, that the ſecond day that Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> appeared, Mr. <hi>Stephens</hi> was in the Chair, as he remembers.</p>
                        <p>
                           <pb n="56" facs="tcp:119492:30"/>Of both which, to make ſome obſervations: Sir <hi>Anthony</hi> ſaith in his Letter, That he knoweth ſir <hi>John</hi> delivered his Petition within the time, according to Articles. And in his Examination, that the ſame was ſo preferred within the time limited by the Articles of <hi>Exon,</hi> as appeareth by the Paſs of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax:</hi> But in neither hath he explained himſelf what he meaneth by (the time limited) for if he intendeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Kalendar time, it is then true; for ſir <hi>John</hi> appearing firſt on the ſixth of <hi>August,</hi> came within the time limited: But then it cannot be true, what Mr. <hi>Michael Herring</hi> hath both ſworn, and affirmed upon his examination, that the Committee refuſed him not for not coming in time. And ſo <hi>Gens contra Gentem.</hi> But if ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> reckoneth but 28 daies to the Month, ſir <hi>John</hi> muſt firſt appear before the 30 of <hi>July,</hi> when the time according to that Act expired; but then the ſuggeſtions of ſir <hi>Anthony</hi>'s own Warrant of the Committee (whereof ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> was one, and preſent) of the fourth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> cannot be true; for that ſurmiſeth, that ſir <hi>John</hi> had not then appeared before any Committee. And by this conſtruction, there is ſir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> the Commiſſioner, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> the Witneſs.</p>
                        <p>He ſaith upon his Examination, The Petition was read, but ſomething therein was diſliked, becauſe ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> did not acknwledge his Delinquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, neither would he take the Covenant and Negative Oath. As touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the refuſal of the Oaths, that could be no cauſe of diſliking his Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; it might be of refuſing his Compoſition, the Oaths being collate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to the Petition. As touching his acknowledgement of Delinquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, it is ſtrange that it is now grown with ſir <hi>Anthony,</hi> a finding of fault (or an occaſion to pick a quarrel) with one that deſerved no favour, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a Character given him of the violenteſt and earlieſt enemy (which was indeed true, let whomſoever give that Character) when as it was the conſtant rule by which that Committee, and ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> himſelf did walk; neither was there any perſon whatſoever that did compound with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it, let him deſerve favour or not.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>But if ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> intended to ſhew him no favour, why did ſir <hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> (for he ſweareth that We did) give him time for eight or ten daies, or fortnight. He further depoſeth that he did not certainly remember; but it was to his cetain remembrance, that by that time, his time given him by his Articles would be out, that (We) might deal with him the better; which if it ſhould be believed to be true (becauſe he ſweareth it) certainly ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> was then too ſevere in his Juſtice, rather injuſt; as he is now too mercifull; neither can he be excuſed of caſting ſnares in ſir <hi>Iohns</hi> way, to ſatisfie his paſſion (for ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> himſelf was then the violenteſt man againſt him) though to the breach of the faith of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and Nation: But we will not take advantage, with an <hi>Habemus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitentem reum,</hi> we will not for his own credit at this time believe him, but do believe Mr. <hi>Iames Aſh,</hi> that time was given unto ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> upon the entreaty of Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſh,</hi> and in hope to draw ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terval unto a ſubmiſſion. Sir <hi>Anthony</hi>'s teſtimony touching ſir <hi>Iohns</hi> carriage at that Committee, hath been before ſufficiently confuted; his opinion that ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> ought to compound (as his expreſſion was upon his Examination) and his deſire to have had ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> admitted to compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as he ought by his Articles, is granted; for ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> ought by his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119492:30"/>
to have been admitted to a Compoſition; but ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> would not compound in ſuch manner as that Committee could compound with him; and therefore he was juſtly denyed ſuch an admiſſion thereunto; but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Rules he was admitted, and might have compounded. As concerning ſir <hi>Anthonies</hi> relation touching the ſale of a Manor of ſir <hi>Iohn Stawels,</hi> it was but a relation of another unſworn, and therefore no evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; but Mr. <hi>Aſh</hi> himſelf hath fully anſwered it, and therefore needs no other at this time, only ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> hath confeſſed that the whole Committee, without a Negative did reſolve to report that carriage of ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> to the Houſe, wherein ſir <hi>Anthony</hi> now ſweareth he then ſaw no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civility; if he did not, where was ſir <hi>Anthonies</hi> Juſtice, when himſelf voted that Report.</p>
            <p>The ſame anſwer reſpectively may be given to ſir <hi>David Watkins</hi>'s Certificate mentioned in the Remonſtrance page 61. and his Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions before this Committee of Parliament, both agreeing; but in this only, that ſir <hi>David</hi> doth now affirm, that he doth account 28 daies to the month, when he ſaith that ſir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> came and preſented his Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition to the Committee within four moneths from the eight of <hi>April;</hi> which likewiſe cannot agree with his Warrant of the fourth of Auguſt often mentioned, he being one of the Committee that granted it; and at that time, it ſeemeth he accounted the Kalender moneths.</p>
            <p>The Remonſtrance page 62. doth ſurmiſe, that the 15. of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1653. the cauſe of Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> whereof the Court of Articles took the Cognizance upon them, came regularly to be heard, but how reagular, or rather how extrajudicial hath been already declared, when the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had reſumed it to themſelves: but that Parliament being diſolved, Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel</hi> took advantage thereof, and by his importunity obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from that Court of Articles, a further, though moſt extrajudicial pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding therein, even to judgment.</p>
            <p>The Truſtees of <hi>Drury</hi> houſe and Purchaſers cannot be blam'd, if to preſerve the honour and credit of Acts of Parliament, they did Petition the then Committe; for Petitions in ſuch manner as the Remonſtrance ſets forth, to prevent ſuch irregularities, eſpecially when that Court was deliberating and adviſing upon their judgement; the Order of which Committee thereon, was as is Remonſtrated; that Colonel <hi>Rous</hi> ſhould report it to the Parliament, with this ſence of the Committee: that the Purchaſers ought to enjoy their Purchaſes, and Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> have ſatisfaction if found within, and ought to have the benefit of Articles; which report made accordingly, and the then Parliament, reading the ſaid ſeveral Votes of Parliament, of the 24 of <hi>February</hi> 1652. touching the ſaid confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſales, and reſuming the cauſe, did reſolve to take the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof on Fryday following. After the reſumption whereof, and during its debate by the Parliament, that Court of Articles took the boldneſs to give that Iudgement; for Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell</hi> at large ſet forth in the Remonſtrance, pag. 65. thereby breaking through Reſolves, Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Acts of Parliament to the contrary; and therefore Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> could not probably conceive that any other beſides himſelf would reſt on, or that the then Parliament would ſuffer their proceedings, or the Judgements or Reſolutions of their Predeceſſors to be queſtioned and annulled by an inferiour juriſdiction; and therefore it was juſtly done by
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119492:31"/>
the Truſtees and Purchaſers, to endeavour to render thoſe illegal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings ſucceſleſs; and for the Parliament, in vindication of their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream power to reſume the debate, touching the Truſtees repreſentation and Purchaſers Petition, the ſooner to declare their reſentment of thoſe proceedings; which they did on the 29 of Auguſt 1653. and upon that debate referred back to the ſame Committee, to conſider of an expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for the Petitioners reliefe; upon which reference, that Committee of Petitions upon conſideration had of that Judgement of the Court of Articles, and the ſeveral Acts conſtituting that Court, and of all the plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and proceedings paſſed in that caſe, thought fit to report that the Purchaſors ought to enjoy the ſame Eſtate, which report the then Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament was pleaſed to confirm, and</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="Parliamentary_resolution">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>Teuſd. the 15 of Septemb. 1653.</date>
                     </dateline>
Reſolved,</opener>
                  <p>That this Houſe do agree with this Report of the Committee, that the Purchaſers of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawel's</hi> Eſtate ſhall quietly poſſeſs and enjoy the ſame, according to their ſeveral contracts made with the Truſtees.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Henry Scobel</hi> Clerk of the Parliament.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And paſſed an Act accordingly in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="Act_of_Parliament">
               <body>
                  <head>Thurſd. the 13. of Octob. 1653 An Act for confirmation of the ſale, of the Lands and Eſtate of Sir <hi>Iohn Stawell,</hi> Knight of the Bath.</head>
                  <p>Be it enacted and deccared by Authority of Parliament, that all ſales made of any Eſtate, Lands, Tenements, Hereditaments, Goods or Chattels of Sir <hi>John Stawell</hi> Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> by vertue or appointment of any Act or Acts of Parliament, are hereby confirmed and eſtabliſhed; and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly all Purchaſers and Buyers of the ſame, ſhall and may have, hold, and quietly enjoy the ſame to them, their Heirs and Aſsigns, according to the Rules, Conditions and Limitations preſcribed in the ſaid Acts, any Law or Judgment to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Hen. Scobell</hi> Clerk of the Parliament.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Notwithſtanding which reference, reſolution, and Act of this ſecond Parliament, in confirmation of the Act and proceedings of the former Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119492:31"/>
and ſale of the Eſtate accordingly, Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> reſteth not, but now pretendeth that the Committee for Petitions purſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d not the intent of that Order of Reference; and draweth that pretence from theſe two Premiſes: The one, becauſe Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> had the (extrajudicial) Judgment of the Court of Articles for part of his Eſtate, therefore this Committee did not purſue the intent of that Order.</p>
            <p>Whereas (not to inſiſt upon the conſequence) the judgment and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the Court of Articles againſt the Purchaſers; being the very cauſe of their Complaint, and againſt which they deſired relief from a ſuperior Court, the Parliament thought fit upon a due conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration to eſtabliſh the enjoyment of the Lands, and by conſequence did lay aſide that Judgment that would have diſturbed it.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John</hi> again ſaith, that in regard the Committee did think fit to confirm the Purchaſers eſtates, therefore they did not purſue the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of that Order touching the Purchaſers relief. As if it were not the beſt and moſt ſit relief to confirm their Eſtates, notwithſtanding this Judgment, that would otherwiſe have taken them away.</p>
            <p>Neither in the judgment of the Parliament it ſelf had that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee not purſued their intent of Reference; for both by a Reſolve and an Act they ſetled the Eſtate accordingly.</p>
            <p>He ſaith, the Purchaſers bargains and contracts could not be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and direct, in regard the ſaid Clauſe of Limitation had debarred the Truſtees themſelves (from whom the Purchaſers claim) in caſe of Articles from any ſuch abſolute Eſtate.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe the Eſtate of the Truſtees had been ſubject to ſuch a truſt in caſe of other men claiming Articles, yet in Sir <hi>Johns</hi> caſe (for the reaſons aforeſaid) there could be no ſuch truſt. State but his caſe, it will ſo appear.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>John</hi> committed Treaſon, and then agreed to ſurrender <hi>Exon,</hi> and to enjoy his Eſtate after Compoſition made within a moneth: But Sir <hi>John</hi> did not make his Compoſition within four moneths, but refuſed to make it according to the Rules of <hi>Goldſmiths Hall,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to petition the Parliament to be admitted to compound at large. The Parliament afterwards (the four moneths expired, and five years paſt, no Compoſition made) upon conſideration of the Articles, and Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> forfeiture of them, enacted the Lands to be ſold.</p>
            <p>Now the truſt upon the rendition being determined with the four moneths, and Sir <hi>Iohns</hi> neglect of making his Compoſition within that time (nay, untill ſale) cannot be annexed to the Act of Sale; neither is there any other truſt of Articles in the caſe of Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> other, then that (loſt) truſt at the rendition. And that the truſt was deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by his not making of his Compoſition within the four moneths, it doth appear by a Judgment of a Court-Martial given about two years after, and by that Army, that beſt knew how to interpret their own Articles. The Judgment is in theſe words.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="finding">
               <body>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:119492:32"/>
                  <head>At a Court-Martial of his Excellencie Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> Knight, Captain-General, &amp;c. Held for the Head-quarters at <hi>White-Hall</hi> the 24 of <hi>February</hi> 1648.</head>
                  <p>VPon the Question, Whether <hi>Robert Barcroft</hi> not compounding, <hi>ſc.</hi> within four moneths after the Rendition of <hi>Exon,</hi> hath loſt the benefit of the Articles of <hi>Exon,</hi> as to his Indempnity againſt <hi>Richards?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It was Reſolved in the affirmative.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>HEN. WHALLEY Iudge-Advocate.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Sir <hi>Johns</hi> Caſe being thus, may we ask him a queſtion or two.</p>
            <p>Since there was no Compoſition made within the four moneths, as by the Articles he ought, we would demand of him, For what cauſe it was not made? Who hindred it?</p>
            <p>If he ſaith the Committee at Goldſmiths Hall; that cannot be; they would willingly have compounded with him, knowing the preſent want of money (as ſir <hi>Anthony Irby</hi> ſweareth) and offered him a Compoſition according to their Rules, and gave him longer time to that end.</p>
            <p>If he ſaith the Parliament; They did not, they were ready, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him five years; nay ſome Members undertook it, if he would have Petitioned to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Neither could his impriſonment be his hindrance, for he was at liberty till the four moneths were expired; and when he was in priſon, his friends would have procured it, if he would but have Petitioned or aſſented there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto.</p>
            <p>But certainly it was his own reſolution to the contrary; that only hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred it, it was that ſtaid him in the Country three moneths and a half of the four, that kept him from Petitioning the Committee at Goldſmiths Hall, untill after the four Moneths expired, or but ſix daies (as himſelf confeſſeth) before the expiration, and not to come there again till war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted. And this his reſolution rendered the endeavours of his friends fruitleſs, and heightned his comportment to an inſolency.</p>
            <p>Again, ſince his actions in <hi>Taunton</hi> are by a cloud of witneſſes proved deſtructive, illegal, and irreligious: we could in a ſecond place demand of him, by what Authority he thus acted? If he ſaith by the late Kings ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, then certainly would not that Kings real intentions or conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy (even in ſir <hi>Iohns</hi> judgement) be for the eſtabliſhment either of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Laws, or Peoples welfare (as ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> pretendeth, Remonſtrance page 75.) if he will ſay, by his own Authority, then did he abuſe his King as groſſely as his Country; for the people conceived thoſe his exorbitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be warranted by the King himſelf: And then ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> hath been faithleſs to King, Parliament, and his own Country.</p>
            <p>To conclude, ſince ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> hath been a depopulator at <hi>Cothelſton,</hi> at <hi>Marſhals Elm</hi> bloudy, a Traitor, a Murtherer, what not in <hi>Taunton?</hi> a breaker of Publick truſt to his Country, of Articles to <hi>Dunſcomb;</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull ſcandalouſly to Mr. <hi>Iohn Aſh,</hi> ruinouſly to Mr. <hi>Long (Et ſi in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratum omnia)</hi> ſince he intrenched on the Priviledg of Parliament, when he
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119492:32"/>
went thence without their leave, and upon the Kings privat Letter only, and hath contemned the Authority thereof at their Barr, in their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee, Iudges, Great Seal, and Sollicitor General; ſithence he hath ſcorned the mercy of the Army, otherwiſe then to uſe it in advance of his Malignant deſigne.</p>
            <p>Can ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> think that the Army would have Articled with him at <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> if they had either known his former, or foreſeen his future miſcarria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; or that the Army in 1652. had in their Petition (mentioned Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance page 72.) any reſpect for him, when they Petitioned to have Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of War made good, according to the intent of them, ſithence ſir <hi>John</hi> hath in not compounding, loſt their benefit, both by their words and intent? or that the late Parliament did upon deſigned, paſſionate, or ſelf-intereſted reports, paſs their Acts or Reſolutions aboveſaid againſt him, when his former offences, his Articles, and after-neglects and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors were then in their conſideration?</p>
            <p>Or can ſir <hi>Iohn</hi> juſtly expect, that this preſent Parliament ſhall (when this his comportment ſhall appear before them) take the Lands from the Purchaſers (perſons innocent, of integrity, and friends to the Publick) and contrary to the Judgements and Acts of former Parliaments (who beſt knew his demerits) and againſt the Law of Publique Sales (which ought to be as firm as the Laws of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> and which nature it ſelf taught the very Heathen to deem inviolable) ſhall ſettle them on ſir <hi>Iohn,</hi> who in Juſtice deſerveth not the mercy of his life?</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:119492:33"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Pag. 5. l. 1. for <hi>Ward</hi> read <hi>Wards.</hi> p. 6. l. 11. <hi>Baker,</hi> r. <hi>Barker.</hi> p. 24. l. 15. <hi>to be honeſt,</hi> r <hi>to honeſt.</hi> p, 25, l. 11. <hi>without,</hi> r. <hi>within.</hi> p. 27. l. 33. <hi>any Act,</hi> r. <hi>ſome Act.</hi> p. 29. l. 36. <hi>as,</hi> r. <hi>was.</hi> p. 31. l. 38. r. <hi>conſtantly compound;</hi> p. 32. l. 3. for <hi>deſign,</hi> r. <hi>deſire;</hi> p. 34. l: 9. for <hi>over,</hi> r. <hi>overt;</hi> l. 17. r. <hi>to their rules;</hi> l. 48 or; Judgment and Sir <hi>David;</hi> p. 39. l. 23. r. annexed, <hi>pag.</hi> 11. p. 41. l. 28. r. admiſſion; p 42. l. 6. for <hi>chaſed,</hi> r. purchaſed; l. 19. r. be foreſeen; p. 45. l. 18. for <hi>greater,</hi> r. great; p. 47. l. 30. for <hi>be,</hi> r. by; l. 40. for <hi>or,</hi> r. againſt; p. 49 l. 13. r. heightned, for them, after that, &amp;c. p. 57. l. 25. r. award; l. 34. for <hi>received,</hi> r. rejected; p. 54. l. 4. for <hi>Goldſmiths-hall,</hi> r. Guildhall; p. 56. l. 13. for <hi>Act</hi> r. Account; l. 14. r. Sir <hi>Anthonies</hi> own warrant, the warrant of the Committee.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
